My dear Frodo:
亲爱的弗罗多
You asked me once...
你曾问过我...
if I had told you everything there was to know about my adventures.
我是不是把全部探险经历都告诉你了
And while I can honestly...
我只能说...
say I have told you...
我告诉了你...
the truth...
真相...
I may not have told you all of it.
但不是全部
I am old now, Frodo.
我老了 弗罗多
I'm not the same Hobbit I once was.
不再是曾经那个霍比特人了
I think...
是时候...
it is time for you to know...
让你知道...
what really happened.
全部真相了
It began...
故事...
long ago...
始于很久前...
in a land far away to the east...
在遥远的东方...
the like of which you will not find in the world today.
现在已无处寻觅
There was the city of Dale.
有一座河谷镇
Its markets known...
城里有知名的...
far and wide.
大型市场
Full of the bounties of vine and vale.
到处都是藤蔓和溪谷
Peaceful and prosperous.
祥和富足
For this city lay before the doors...
因为这座城市...
of the greatest kingdom in Middle-earth:
横亘在中土最伟大的王国门外
Erebor.
伊鲁柏
Stronghold of Thror...
最强大的...
King Under the Mountain. Mightiest...
山下之王索尔...
of the Dwarf Lords.
的矮人王国
Thror ruled with utter surety...
索尔有着绝对的统治权...
never doubting his house would endure...
从没有人质疑他王权的延续...
for his line lay secure...
因为他的统治...
in the lives of his son...
有他儿子...
and grandson.
还有孙子来继承
Ah, Frodo. Erebor.
啊 弗罗多 说到伊鲁柏
Built deep within the mountain itself...
它建在山脉内部...
the beauty of this fortress city was legend.
是座传奇般美丽的要塞
Its wealth lay in the earth...
它的财富埋藏在地下...
in precious gems hewn...
岩石中随处可见宝石...
from rock and in great seams of gold...
黄金像河水一样奔流...
running like rivers through stone.
储量丰富
The skill of the Dwarves...
矮人们加工钻石 祖母绿...
was unequaled, fashioning objects...
红宝石 蓝宝石的技艺..
of great beauty...
如同美人的饰物般...
out of diamond, emerald, ruby and sapphire.
精湛得无与伦比
Ever they delved deeper...
越挖越深...
down into the dark.
深入黑暗
And that is where they found it.
然后 在那里 发现了它
The Heart of the Mountain.
山脉之心
The Arkenstone.
阿肯宝石
Thror named it "The King's Jewel. "
索尔取名为"国王的珠宝"
He took it as a sign, a sign that his right to rule...
他把它当做一种象征...
was divine.
天赐统治权的象征
All would pay...
所有人...
homage to him.
都要向他表示尊敬
Even the great...
包括伟大的...
Elven King, Thranduil.
精灵王 瑟兰督伊
As the great wealth of the Dwarves grew...
随着矮人们的财富增长...
their store of good will ran thin.
他们的良知却日渐淡薄
No one knows exactly what began the rift.
没有人知道争议究竟因何而起
The Elves say...
精灵们说...
the Dwarves stole their treasure.
是矮人们偷了他们的宝藏
The Dwarves tell another tale.
矮人们则另有论断
They say the Elf King refused to give them their rightful pay.
他们说是因为精灵王拒绝支付报酬
It is sad, Frodo, how old alliances...
很可悲 弗罗多 长久的联盟...
can be broken.
为何会分裂
How friendships between peoples can be lost.
人们之间的友谊会灭失
And for what?
为何会灭失?
Slowly the days turned sour...
渐渐的 日子不再好过...
and the watchful nights closed in.
暗夜即将来临
Thror's love of gold...
索尔对黄金的痴迷...
had grown too fierce.
走火入魔
A sickness had begun to grow within him.
他产生了邪念
It was a sickness of the mind.
那是心灵的邪念
And where sickness thrives...
而邪念滋生之处...
bad things will follow.
罪恶也随之而来
The first they heard was a noise...
首先大家听到了...
like a hurricane coming down...
像飓风一样的声音...
from the North.
从北方袭来
The pines on the mountain creaked and cracked...
山丘上的松树...
in the hot, dry wind.
在炎热干燥的风中吱嘎碎裂
Balin, sound the alarm.
巴林 发警报
Call out the guard. Do it now!
召集守卫 快!
What is it?
怎么回事?
Dragon.
龙
Dragon!
龙!
He was...
那是...
a firedrake from the North.
北方来的火龙
Smaug...
史矛革...
had come.
来了
Such wanton death...
那天死者...
was dealt that day.
不计其数
For this city of Men was nothing...
史矛革视人族城镇...
to Smaug.
为无物
His eye...
他...
was set on another prize.
另有目标
For dragons...
因为龙...
covet gold...
对黄金...
with a dark and...
有非常狂热的...
fierce desire.
贪念
Aah!
啊!
No!
不!
Come on.
走啊
Erebor was lost.
伊鲁柏失陷
For a dragon...
因为龙...
will guard his plunder...
会守卫他的战利品...
as long as he lives.
不死不离
Run for your lives!
逃命去吧!
Ah! Help us!
啊! 帮帮我们!
Thranduil would not risk the lives of his kin against...
瑟兰督伊不会让自己的族人...
the wrath of the dragon.
冒性命之险去对抗龙的残暴
No help came from the Elves...
那天精灵方未施援手...
that day, nor any day since.
从那以后再也没有
Robbed of their homeland...
被赶出了自己的家乡...
the Dwarves of Erebor wandered the wilderness...
伊鲁柏的矮人们流离失所...
a once mighty people brought low.
曾经高傲的人们陷入困境
The young Dwarf prince took work where he could find it...
年轻的矮人王子竭尽所能...
laboring in the villages of Men.
在人族村庄中劳作
But always he remembered...
但他一直没有忘记...
the mountain smoke beneath the moon...
月下的山丘升起的黑烟...
the trees like torches blazing bright.
树木像火把一样燃炽
For he had seen dragon fire...
因为他目睹了...
in the sky...
漫天的龙火...
and a city turned to ash.
将一座城市变为灰烬
And he never forgave...
他永远不会原谅...
and he never forgot.
也永远不会忘记
Far away, in another corner of the world...
而在远方 在世界的另一个角落...
dragons were...
龙只是...
only make-believe.
存在于传说中
Up they go!
飞上去喽!
A party trick...
在仲夏夜的聚会上...
conjured by Wizards...
由巫师变出来的...
on Midsummer's Eve.
魔术里
No more frightening...
还不如魔法仙尘...
than fairy dust.
可怕
Bilbo!
比尔博!
And that, my dear Frodo...
而我 亲爱的弗罗多...
is where I come in.
就此参与了这段传奇
Bilbo! Bilbo.
比尔博! 比尔博
It was the beginning of an unlikely friendship...
一段伴随了我一辈子却有些意外的友谊...
that has lasted all my life.
就是那样开始的
But it is not the start of my story. For me, it began...
而并不是我故事真正的开始 对我来说 应该从...
Well, it began as you might expect.
刚开始 可能跟你期待的一样
In a hole in the ground, there lived...
地上的洞穴里 住着一个...
a Hobbit.
霍比特人
Not a nasty, dirty, wet hole full of worms and oozy smells.
并不是杂乱 肮脏 充满怪味和虫子的潮湿洞穴
This was a Hobbit hole.
是个霍比特式洞穴
And that means good food, a warm hearth...
那就意味着高品质的食物 温暖的壁炉...
and all the comforts of home.
以及一切组成家的舒适条件
Thank you.
谢谢
What's this?
这是什么?
That is private.
这是私人物品
Keep your sticky paws off.
把你的手爪子拿开
It's not ready yet.
还没准备好呢
Not ready for what?
准备做什么?
Reading.
给人看
What on earth are these?
这些到底都是什么?
Replies to the party invitations.
对聚会邀请函的回复
Ah. Good gracious. Is it today?
啊 太好了 是今天吗?
They all say they're coming.
他们都说会来
Except for the Sackville-Bagginses, who are demanding you ask them in person.
除了塞克维尔巴金斯一家 他们要求你单独邀请
Are they, indeed? Over my...
是吗 真的? 等我...
- dead body.  - They'd probably find that...
- 死了吧  - 他们可能认为...
quite agreeable.
这样是可以的
They seem to think you have tunnels overflowing with gold.
他们好像认为你有些地道满藏着金子
It was one small chest, hardly overflowing.
只有一个小箱子 根本没满
And it still smells of Troll.
还带着食人妖的味道
What on earth are you doing?
你究竟在干什么?
Taking precautions. You know...
预防措施 其实...
I caught her making off with the silverware once.
我曾经有一次看到她带着银餐具走掉
- Who?  - Lobelia Sackville-Baggins.
- 谁?  - 罗贝莉娅・塞克维尔巴金斯
She had all my spoons stuffed in her pocket. Ha!
她把我所有的勺子都装进了她口袋里 哈!
Dreadful woman.
讨厌的女人
Make sure you keep an eye on her after I'm...
得留神盯着她 等我...
When I'm... When I'm...
等我... 等我...
When you're what?
等你什么?
It's nothing. Nothing.
没事了 没事
You know, some people are beginning to wonder about you, Uncle.
有些人开始对你很好奇了 叔叔
- Huh?  - They think you're becoming odd.
- 啊?  - 他们认为你变怪了
Odd? Oh. Hm.
怪了? 哦 嗯
Unsociable.
孤僻
Unsociable, me? Nonsense.
我 孤僻? 开玩笑
Be a good lad and put that...
乖乖的...
on the gate.
把这个钉到门上去
Do you think he'll come?
你觉得他会来吗?
Who?
谁?
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Oh... ho. He wouldn't miss a chance to let off his Whizpoppers. He'll give us...
哦... 哈 他可不会放过能表演他的小把戏的机会 他会给我们...
quite a show, you'll see.
演一场好戏的 等着吧
- Right, then. I'm off.  - Off to where?
- 好吧 那么 我就走了  - 去哪?
East-farthing Woods. I'm going to surprise him.
东区森林 我要去给他个惊喜
Well, go on, then. You don't want to be late.
哦 那你去吧 你肯定不想迟到
He doesn't approve of being late. Oh, no. Not that I...
他没迟到 哦 不 我也...
ever was.
没迟到过
In those days, I was always on time.
那个时候 我总是很准时
I was entirely respectable.
非常受人尊敬
And nothing unexpected...
我身上从没发生过...
ever happened.
意料之外的事情
- Good morning.  - What do you mean?
- 早上好  - 你什么意思?
Do you wish me a good morning or do you mean that it is a good morning...
你是希望我早上好还是不管我想不想要...
whether I want it or not?
我的早上都会好?
Or perhaps you mean to say that you feel good on this particular morning?
或者你可能是想说这个早上你感觉非常好?
Or are you simply stating that this is a morning to be good on? Hm?
再或者你只是单纯的想表示这个早上会好? 嗯?
All of them at once, I suppose.
我觉得 以上全对
Hmm.
嗯
Can I help you?
我能帮你吗?
That remains to be seen.
有待观察
I'm looking for someone to share in an adventure.
我在寻找人一起探险
An adventure?
探险?
No, I don't imagine anyone west of Bree would have much interest in adventures.
不 我觉得布理以西没有人会对探险感兴趣
Nasty, disturbing, uncomfortable things.
邋遢 烦人 不爽的事情
Make you late for dinner. Heh, heh.
让人吃不上晚餐 嘿嘿
Mm.
嗯
Huh.
哈
Oh. Ah.
哦 哈
Good morning.
早上好
To think that I should have lived to be "good morninged"...
真没想到有一日 我会被贝拉多娜・图克的儿子...
by Belladonna Took's son as if I were selling buttons at the door.
用一句 "早上好" 打发走 就好像我是上门推销扣子的人
Beg your pardon?
你说什么?
You've changed, and not entirely for the better...
你变了 可是并不是完全往好的方向...
Bilbo Baggins.
比尔博・巴金斯
I'm sorry, do I know you?
抱歉 我认识你吗?
Well, you know my name, although you don't remember I belong to it.
呃 你知道我的名字 可是你对不上号了
I'm Gandalf.
我是甘道夫
And Gandalf means...
甘道夫就是...
me.
我
Gandalf? Not Gandalf the wandering Wizard...
甘道夫? 不是那个能...
who made such excellent...
能变非常棒的烟火的游者巫师...
- fireworks? Old Took used to have them on Midsummer's Eve.  - Heh, heh. Ahem.
- 甘道夫吧? 老图克经常在仲夏夜放那个  - 嘿嘿 嗯
No idea you were still in business.
不知道你还在干这个呢
And where else should I be?
那我应该干什么去了?
Where else...? Ahem.
干什么...? 嗯
Well, I'm pleased to find you remember something about me...
呃 很高兴你还记得有关我的事情...
even if it's only my fireworks.
虽然只记得我的烟火
Yes. Well, that's decided.
对 是的 那就决定了
It'll be very good for you...
这会对你很好...
and most amusing for me.
让我觉得很有趣
I shall inform the others.
我应该通知其他人了
Inform the who? What? No. No. No... Wait.
通知谁? 什么? 不 不 不... 等等
We do not want...
我们这的人不要...
any adventures here, thank you. Not today. Not...
探险 谢谢 今天不要 以后...
I suggest you try Over the Hill or Across the Water.
我建议你去山的那边或者海的对岸
Good morning.
早上好
Morning!
早上好!
Twelve. There we go. Have a very good day.
十二个钱 给您 祝您愉快
Chum.
谢谢
Hello, Mr. Bilbo. Here.
你好 比尔博先生 来看看
Have a feel of me tubers. Nice and firm, they are.
摸摸我这些球薯 又好又脆 看看
- Just come in from West Farthing.  - Very impressive, Mr. Worrywort.
- 刚从西区运来的  - 很好 瓦利沃特先生
Now, I don't suppose you've seen a Wizard lurking around these parts?
这个 我估计你没看到一个巫师藏在这附近吧?
A tall fellow.
是个高个子
Long, gray beard.
长长的 灰色胡子
Pointy hat.
带着尖尖的帽子
Can't say I have.
没见过那样的
Dwalin, at your service.
德瓦林 为您效劳
Hm. Uh...
嗯 呃...
Bilbo Baggins, at yours.
比尔博・巴金斯 也为您效劳
Do we...
我们...
know each other?
认识吗?
No.
不认识
Which way, laddie?
在哪 老弟?
Is it down here?
是在这下面吗?
Is what...
什么在...
down where?
哪里下面?
Supper.
晚餐
He said there'd be food and lots of it.
他说这里有吃的 而且有很多
He... He said? Who said?
他... 他说? 谁说?
Mmm.
嗯
Very good, this. Any more?
很好吃 这个 还有吗?
What? Oh, yes, yes.
什么? 哦 有 是
Ah.
呃
Help yourself.
请自便
Hmm. It's just that, um, I wasn't expecting company.
嗯 只是 呃 我没想到会有人来
That'll be the door.
来客人了
Balin...
巴林...
at your service.
为您效劳
Good evening.
晚上好
Yes. Yes, it is.
是的 今晚很好
- Though I think it might rain later.  - Hm?
- 但恐怕一会儿要下雨  - 嗯?
Am I late?
我迟到了吗?
Late for what?
迟到什么?
Oh!
喔
Ha, ha!
哈 哈!
Evening, brother.
晚上好 兄弟
By my beard...
我发誓...
you're shorter and wider than last we met.
你比上次见面时更矮更胖了
Wider, not shorter.
胖了 没有矮
Sharp enough for both of us.
看上去依然神采奕奕
Uh, excuse me? Sorry, I hate to interrupt.
抱歉? 对不起 我不想打扰
But the thing is, I'm not entirely sure you're in the right house.
但是 你们应该走错人家了吧
- Have you eaten?  - It's not that I don't like visitors...
- 你吃饭了么?  - 我不是不喜欢客人...
I like visitors...
我跟隔壁的...
as much as the next Hobbit.
霍比特人一样好客
But I do like to know them before they come visiting.
不过我还是喜欢已经认识的客人
- What is this?  - I don't know.
- 这是啥?  - 没见过
- I think it's cheese. Gone blue.  - It's riddled with mold.
- 我觉得是奶酪 变蓝了  - 那是发霉了
The thing is, I don't know either of you. Not in the slightest. I don't mean...
是这样 我不认识你们俩 一点都不认识 我不想...
to be blunt, but I had to speak my mind.
没礼貌 不过还是得说出来
- I'm sorry.  - You think...?
- 对不起  - 你认为...?
Apology accepted.
原谅你了
- Ah.  - Now, fill it up, brother...
- 啊  - 快 倒满 兄弟...
don't stint.
别小气
- You wanna get stuck in?  - I could eat again if you insist, brother.
- 你想撑死啊?  - 你想看吗 我还能再吃一遍
- Fili.  - And Kili.
- 菲力  - 还有奇力
At your service.
为您效劳
You must be Mr. Boggins.
你一定是巴金斯先生
Nope! You can't come in. You've come to the wrong house.
不是! 你们不能进来 你们走错了
What?
什么?
- Has it been canceled?  - No one told us.
- 取消了吗?  - 没人通知我们
No, nothing's been canceled.
不 没有取消
That's a relief.
那就好
Careful with these.
小心放置
I just had them sharpened.
我刚磨过的
- It's nice, this place.  - Yeah.
- 这地方不错  - 是啊
- Did you do it yourself?  - What? No, it's been in the family for years.
- 你自己建的?  - 什么? 不 家族流传了很多年了
That's my mother's glory box. Can you please not do that?
那是我妈妈的嫁妆箱 不要这样好吗?
Fili, Kili. Come on, give us a hand.
菲力 奇力 过来搭把手
Mr. Dwalin. Ha, ha.
德瓦林先生 哈哈
Shove this in the hallway. Otherwise we'll never get everyone in.
把这个推到走廊去 不然就不能全进来了
"Everyone"? How many more are there? Where do you want this?
"全进来"? 还有多少? 你要搬哪去?
- Oh, no.  - It's really heavy.
- 不行  - 太重了
No. No. There's nobody home!
不许进来 家里没人!
Go away and bother somebody else.
找别人称兄道弟去吧
There's far too many Dwarves in my dining room as it is.
餐厅里的矮人多得装不下了
If this is some clot-head's idea of a joke...
如果这是哪个榆木脑袋搞的恶作剧...
I can only say it is in very...
我只能说...
poor taste.
太没品了
Get off...
下去...
you big lump!
你个大块头!
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Excuse me, that's my chicken. Um...
抱歉 那是我的鸡肉 呃...
If... If you don't... That's my wine. Excuse me!
别... 别碰... 那是我的酒 拜托!
He's got an injury.
他受伤了
You mean the ax in his head?
你指他头上的斧子?
Dead? No, only between his ears.
死了? 不 只是砍在脑门上
His legs work fine.
还能走路呢
Put those back.
把这些东西放回去
Put that back.
放回去
Not the jam.
别拿果酱
Excuse me. Excuse me.
拜托 拜托
It's a tad excessive, isn't it? Have you got a cheese knife?
稍微有点多了 对吧? 你有奶酪刀吗?
- "Cheese knife"? He eats it by the block.  - Ugh.
- "奶酪刀"? 他整块的吃  - 呃
No, that's Grandpa Mungo's chair... No, so is that. Take it back, please.
不 那是蒙哥祖父的椅子... 不行 那个也是 拜托放回去
- I cannot hear what you're saying.  - It's an antique. Not for sitting on.
- 我听不到你说什么  - 这是古董 不是用来坐的
That is a book, not a coaster. And put that map down.
那是书 不是杯托 地图也放下
- Excuse me, Mr. Gandalf?  - Yes?
- 抱歉 甘道夫先生?  - 怎么?
May I tempt you with a cup of chamomile?
要来一杯甘菊茶吗?
Oh, no, thank you, Dori. A little red wine for me, I think.
不 谢谢了 朵力 还是来杯红酒好了
Whoop! Mind out.
哦! 小心
Uh, Fili, Kili. Uh...
呃 菲力 奇力 呃...
Oin, Gloin.
欧因 葛罗因
Dwalin, Balin, Bifur, Bofur, Bombur...
德瓦林 巴林 毕佛 波佛 庞博...
- Dori, Nori. Ori!  - No. Not my prizewinners, thank you.
- 朵力 诺力 欧力!  - 不 不许吃我的得奖作品 谢谢
No, thank you.
放手 谢谢
Yes, you're quite right, Bifur.
嗯 说的很对 毕佛
We appear to be one Dwarf short.
好像还少了一个矮人
He is late, is all. He traveled north to a meeting of our kin. He will come.
他只是迟到了 他去北方跟同族开会了 他会来的
Mr. Gandalf? A little glass of red wine, as requested.
甘道夫先生? 您要的红酒来了
It's got a fruity bouquet.
有一股水果的芳香
Oh. Cheers.
哦 干杯
Bombur's on his second leg of lamb already.
庞博在吃第二条羊腿了
No chance. Not from that distance.
不可能 那么远肯定接不住
Wanna bet? Bombur...
打赌?庞博...
catch!
接着!
I'll help you with that.
我来帮你
Oh, you great...
哦 你这...
galumphing git!
大饭桶
Who wants an ale? There you go.
谁还要麦芽酒? 给你
Over here, brother.
伙计 这里
I said have another drink...
你得再喝一杯...
Here you go.
给你
Ale on the count of three!
数三声干杯!
One...
一...
- two...  - Up!
- 二...  - 干杯!
I knew you had it in you!
就知道你会这样!
Excuse me, that is a doily, not a dishcloth.
抱歉 这是杯垫 不是抹布
But it's full of holes.
都破成这样了
It's supposed to look like that. It's crochet.
它就应该长这样 针织的
And a wonderful game it is too, if you've got the balls for it.
如果你喜欢的话 编织也是很好玩的
Bebother and confusticate these Dwarves!
这些矮人真讨厌!
My dear Bilbo, what on earth is the matter?
亲爱的比尔博 你这是怎么了?
What's the matter? I'm surrounded by Dwarves.
怎么了? 我家里一堆矮人
What are they doing here?
他们来这干什么?
Oh, they're quite a merry gathering once you get used to them.
习惯了就会觉得他们是很欢乐的一群人了
I don't want to get used to them.
我不想习惯他们
Look at the state of my kitchen. There's mud trod into the carpet.
瞧瞧我的厨房 地毯上踩的全是泥巴
They've pillaged the pantry.
储藏室也被一扫而光
I won't tell you what they've done in the bathroom.
更别说他们在厕所干的事情了
They've destroyed the plumbing. I don't understand what they're doing in my house!
下水道都坏了 真不知道他们来我家干什么!
Excuse me. I'm sorry to interrupt, but what should I do with my plate?
抱歉 打扰一下 这盘子该怎么处理?
Here you go, Ori. Give it to me.
这儿 欧力 给我吧
Take that back.
放回来
Excuse me.
拜托
That's my mother's...
这是我母亲的...
West Farthing pottery. It's over...
西域陶瓷 已经有...
100 years old!
100多年历史了!
And can you...
你们能...
not do that?
不这样么?
You'll blunt them.
刀子会变钝的
Ooh. Do you hear that, lads?
听他说啥了吗 小子们?
He says...
他说...
we'll blunt the knives.
我们会把刀弄钝
# Blunt the knives, bend the forks #
# 刀子敲钝 叉子掰弯 #
# Smash the bottles and burn the corks #
# 瓶子打破 木塞烧了 #
# Chip the glasses and crack the plates #
# 杯子敲烂 盘子摔碎 #
# That's what Bilbo Baggin hates#
# 气得比尔博・巴金斯火冒三丈 #
# Cut the cloth, tread on the fat #
# 衣服撕碎 满地油腻 #
# Leave the bones on the bedroom mat #
# 吃剩骨头 垫子上放 #
# Pour the milk on the pantry floor #
# 牛奶打开 倒在地上 #
# Splash the wine #
# 酒渍溅到 #
# on every door #
# 每扇门上 #
# Dump the crocks in a boiling bowl #
# 陶瓷摔碎 扔碗里煮 #
# Pound them up with a thumping pole #
# 拿个棍子 全部打碎 #
# When you're finished #
# 完事之后 #
# If they are whole #
# 若还完整 #
# Send them down the hall to roll #
# 全扔客厅 散落一地 #
# That's what Bilbo Baggins hates #
# 气得比尔博・巴金斯火冒三丈 #
Bilbo.
比尔博
He is here.
他来了
Gandalf.
你好 甘道夫
I thought you said...
我记得你说...
this place would be easy to find...
这里很好找...
I lost my way, twice.
但我迷路了 两次
I wouldn't have found it at all had it not been for that mark on the door.
要不是门上有标记 我绝对找不到这儿
Mark? There's no mark on that door. It was painted a week ago.
标记? 门上没有标记 一周前刚漆过
There is a mark. I put it there myself.
有的 我标记上去的
Bilbo Baggins, allow me to introduce the leader of our company:
比尔博・巴金斯 允许我向你介绍这些伙伴的领袖:
Thorin Oakenshield.
索林・橡木盾
So...
那么...
this is the Hobbit.
你就是那个霍比特人
Tell me, Mr. Baggins, have you done much fighting?
和我说说 巴金斯先生 以前打过仗吗?
- Pardon me? Ax or sword?
- 你说什么?  - 用斧子还是剑?
What's your weapon of choice?
喜欢用什么武器?
Well, I do have some skill at conkers, if you must know...
呃 非要问的话 我对扔板栗颇有心得...
but I fail to see why that's relevant.
但这有什么联系吗?
Thought as much.
如我所料
He looks more like a grocer than a burglar.
比起飞贼 他更像个杂货商
What news...
伊瑞德隆会议...
from the meeting in Ered Luin? Did they all come?
传来什么消息? 他们都来了吗?
- Aye. Envoys from all seven kingdoms.  - All of them!
- 七个王国的使者都来了  - 全都来了!
And what did the Dwarves of the Iron Hills say?
铁丘陵的矮人怎么说?
Is Dain with us?
戴因来吗?
They will not come.
他们不愿意来
They say this quest...
他们说这次探险...
is ours and ours alone.
仅仅是我们自己的事
You're going on a quest?
你们要去探险?
Bilbo, my dear fellow, let us have a little more light.
比尔博 亲爱的伙计 再多点几盏灯吧
Far to the east...
在遥远的东方...
over ranges and rivers...
穿越无数的山脉河流...
beyond woodlands and wastelands...
跨过无尽的森林和荒漠...
lies a single, solitary peak.
有一座孤峰傲立着
"The Lonely Mountain."
"孤山"
Aye, Oin has read...
没错 欧因读到过...
the portents, and the portents say it is time.
预言的征兆 征兆显示时机已到
Ravens have been seen...
如预言所述...
flying back to the mountain, as it was foretold.
渡鸦飞回山中
"When the birds of yore return...
"昔日的鸟儿回归...
to Erebor...
伊鲁柏之时...
the reign of the beast...
魔兽的统治...
will end. "
将会结束"
- Uh, what beast?  - That would be a reference...
- 什么魔兽?  - 指的是...
to Smaug the Terrible...
恐惧之王史矛革...
chiefest and greatest...
我们时代...
calamity of our age.
最可怕的灾难
Airborne fire-breather.
会飞的喷火者
Teeth like razors...
剃刀般尖锐的牙齿...
claws like meat hooks.
肉钩一样的爪子
Fond of precious metals.
极度喜爱贵重金属
I know what a dragon is.
我知道龙长啥样
I'm not afraid. I'm up for it.
我才不怕 我准备好了
I'll give him a taste of Dwarfish iron right up his jacksie!
我要让他的菊花好好尝尝矮人钢铁的厉害!
Good lad, Ori!
好小子 欧力!
Sit down.
坐下
The task would be difficult...
即使整支军队出动...
with an army behind us...
任务也很艰巨...
but we number just 13.
何况我们只有13个人
And not 13 of the best...
而且其中还有歪瓜裂枣...
nor brightest.
傻头傻脑的
Hey, who are you calling dim?
喂 你说谁傻瓜呢?
Sorry, what did he say?
不好意思 他刚说什么?
We may be few in number...
我们虽然人少...
but we're fighters, all of us...
但我们是战士 所有人...
to the last Dwarf.
都会奋战到底
And you forget, we have a Wizard in our company.
你们还忘了 我们有巫师结伴
Gandalf will have killed hundreds of dragons.
甘道夫可以杀掉上百条龙
Oh, well, no. I wouldn't say...
这个 我不敢说...
- How many, then?  - What?
- 那有多少?  - 什么?
How many dragons have you killed?
你杀过多少条龙?
Go on.
说啊
Give us a number.
给个数
Excuse me. Please.
拜托 别吵了
If we have read these signs...
如果我们能看见这些预兆...
do you not think others will have read them too?
难道别的种族就看不出来吗?
Rumors have begun to spread.
谣言已经传开
The dragon, Smaug, has not been seen for 60 years.
那巨龙史矛革已经有60年无人见过
Eyes look east to the mountain, assessing...
许多人都觊觎着东方那片土地 思索...
wondering, weighing the risk.
徘徊 权衡利弊
Perhaps the vast wealth of our people now lies unprotected.
或许我们的宝藏现在无人看守
Do we sit back while others claim what is rightfully ours?
我们是坐视别人抢走我们的东西?
Or do we seize this chance...
还是抓住机会...
to take back Erebor?
夺回伊鲁柏?
You forget, the Front Gate is sealed.
可是 要塞的正门被堵死了
There is no way...
已经没有路...
into the mountain.
可以进山了
That, my dear Balin, is not entirely true.
这可未必 亲爱的巴林
How came you by this?
你怎么会有这个?
It was given to me...
是你父亲...
by your father.
给我的
By Thrain.
索恩给我的
For safekeeping.
要我保管
It is yours...
现在...
now.
是你的了
If there is a key...
如果有钥匙...
there must be a door.
肯定就有门
These runes...
这些符语...
speak of a hidden passage to the Lower Halls.
暗示有个密门通向要塞大厅
There's another way in.
有别的方法进去
Well, if we can find it, but Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
能找到最好 但矮人的门关着的时候看不见
The answer lies hidden somewhere in this map...
位置就在这张地图上...
and I do not have the skill to find it.
但是我不知道如何找到它
But there are others in Middle-earth who can.
但是中土世界有人可以
The task I have in mind will require a great deal of stealth...
我想的计划需要做的非常隐蔽...
and no small amount of courage.
并且需要巨大的勇气
But if we are careful and clever, I believe that it can be done.
如果我们够细心够机灵 我相信是可以做到的
That's why we need a burglar.
所以我们需要一个飞贼
Hmm. And a good one too. An expert, I'd imagine.
要一个本领高强的飞贼 最好是专家
And are you?
你是吗?
Am I what?
我是什么?
He said he's an expert.
他说他就是一个专家
Me? No. No, no, no. I'm not a burglar. I've never stolen a thing in my life.
我? 不不 我不是飞贼 我这辈子从未偷过东西
Well, I'm afraid I have to agree with Mr. Baggins.
我也同意巴金斯先生
He's hardly burglar material.
他绝对不是当飞贼的料
Nope.
不是
Aye, the Wild is no place for gentle folk who can neither fight nor fend for themselves.
是啊 既不会战斗也不会防御的软弱之人无法在野外生存
He's just fine.
他也就一般
Enough!
够了!
If I say Bilbo Baggins...
我说比尔博・巴金斯是...
is a burglar, then a burglar...
飞贼 那他...
he is.
就是
Hobbits are light on their feet...
霍比特人的脚步轻盈...
In fact, they can pass unseen by most, if they choose.
如果他们想 大多数人都注意不到他们
And, while the dragon is accustomed to the smell of Dwarf...
虽然龙对于矮人气味十分熟悉...
the scent of a Hobbit is all but unknown to him...
但是霍比特人的气息 它就完全不了解...
which gives us a distinct advantage.
这会给我们带来很大优势
You asked me to find the 14th member of this
你让我寻找第14名成员
company and I have chosen Mr. Baggins.
我推荐巴金斯先生
There's a lot more to him than appearances suggest.
他还是很能干的 别被外表迷惑了
And he's got a great deal more to offer than any of you know.
他所能做的 完全超乎你们得想象
Including himself.
他自己也不知道
You must trust me on this.
在这点上 你得相信我
Very well.
好吧
- We will do it your way.  - No, no.
- 就按你的来做  - 不 不
- Give him the contract.  - We're in. We're off.
- 把合同给他  - 算我们一个
It's just the usual.
这是惯例条款
Summary of out-of-pocket expenses...
包括总体支出...
time required, remuneration...
所需时间 报酬...
funeral arrangements, so forth.
葬礼安排 等等
Funeral arrangements?
葬礼安排?
I cannot guarantee his safety.
我可不能保证他小命安全
Understood.
了解
Nor will I be responsible for his fate.
未来我也不会照顾他
Agreed.
同意
"Terms: Cash on
"条款: 事成付款
delivery, up to but not exceeding one-fourteenth of total profit, if any."
报酬将达到并不超过总收益的十四分之一 如果有收益"
Hmm. Seems fair.
很公平
"Present company shall not be liable for injuries inflicted by...
"本队将不对成员未来所受的各种伤负责...
or sustained as a consequence thereof, including, but not limited to lacerations...
这些伤害包括但不局限于撕裂伤...
evisceration..."
内脏伤..."
Incineration?
火葬?
Aye. He'll melt the flesh off your bones in the blink of an eye.
对 那龙也许眨眼间就把你的血肉全部烧了
- You all right, laddie?  - Huh? Yeah.
- 你没事吧?  - 嗯? 我很好
Feel a bit faint.
头有点晕
- Think furnace with wings.  - Air.
- 想象一下会飞的火炉  - 新鲜空气
I need air.
我需要缓口气
Flash of light, searing pain, then poof.
炽烈的亮光 灼烧的疼痛 然后噗的一下
You're nothing more than a pile of ash.
你就成了一堆炭灰了
Nope.
不好
Oh, very helpful, Bofur.
你真会帮倒忙 波佛
I'll be all right. Just let me sit quietly for a moment.
我没事的 让我安静的待会就行了
You've been sitting quietly for far too long.
你太沉溺于这种安逸的生活了
Tell me, when did doilies and your mother's dishes...
你怎么对那些杯垫和你老妈的碟子...
become so important to you?
看得如此重要?
I remember a young Hobbit who was always
我记忆中的那个小霍比特人总是
running off in search of Elves in the woods.
在林子间寻找精灵们
Who would stay out late, come home after dark...
总是玩到很晚回家...
trailing mud and twigs and fireflies.
全身都是泥巴 树枝 还有萤火虫
A young Hobbit who would have liked nothing better...
那个年轻的霍比特人 总是想要...
than to find out what was beyond the borders of the Shire.
探索夏尔外面的世界
The world is not in your books and maps.
世界可不是一本书或是一张地图
It's out there.
它在屋外
I can't just go running off into the blue.
我不能就这样无声无息地和你们走
I am a Baggins of Bag-end.
我是住在袋底洞的巴金斯
You are also a Took.
但你也是图克家族的
Did you know that your great-great-great-great-uncle Bullroarer Took...
你知道吗 你的曾曾曾曾伯父 吼牛・图克...
was so large, he could ride a real horse?
体型大得能够骑一匹马吗?
- Yes.  - Yes, well, he could.
- 知道  - 当然 他可以
In the Battle of Green Fields, he charged the Goblin ranks.
绿原之战中 他冲向哥布林大军
He swung his club so hard, it knocked the Goblin king's head clean off...
他的力量之大 用棒子生生把敌方国王脑袋敲下来...
and it sailed 100 yards through the air and went down a rabbit hole.
滚了一百多码才掉到一个兔子窝里
And thus, the battle was won.
他们赢得了战役
And the game of golf invented at the same time.
从那以后 有人因此发明了高尔夫(哥布林国王名叫高尔夫裘)
I do believe you made that up.
我知道你是乱编的
Well, all good stories deserve embellishment.
所有精彩的故事都需要润润色嘛
You'll have a tale or two to tell of your own when you come back.
如果你回来了 那你也有自己的传奇故事了
Can you promise that I will come back?
你能保证我能安全回来?
No.
不能
And if you do...
如果你能回得来...
you will not be the same.
你绝对不会和现在一样
That's what I thought.
我也同意
Sorry, Gandalf, I can't sign this.
不好意思 甘道夫 我不能签这个
You've got the wrong Hobbit.
你找错霍比特人了
It appears we have lost our burglar.
我们的飞贼似乎不干了
Probably for the best.
也许这样也好
The odds were always against us.
事事总不能如意啊
After all, what are we?
说到底 我们是什么?
Merchants, miners...
商人 矿工...
tinkers, toy-makers.
铁匠 做玩具的
Heh, heh. Hardly the stuff of legend.
看起来不太像是一群英雄们
There are a few warriors amongst us.
我们中间还是有战士的
Old warriors.
残兵败将
I would take each and every one of these Dwarves...
比起铁丘陵的矮人军队
over an army from the Iron Hills.
我宁可有这些人的追随
For when I called upon them, they answered.
因为在我号召时他们一定能回应
Loyalty, honor...
忠诚 荣耀...
a willing heart.
热诚
I can ask no more than that.
我觉得这些就够了
You don't have to do this.
你不必亲自去
You have a choice.
你可以选择不去
You've done honorably by our people.
我们族人拥戴你 愿意受你领导
You have built a new life for us in the Blue Mountains.
是你在蓝山开辟新的居住地
A life of peace and plenty.
过着和平富裕的生活
A life that is worth more than all the gold in Erebor.
我觉得这一切比伊鲁柏的金子更宝贵
From my grandfather to my father, this has come to me.
从我的爷爷传到我父亲 现在到我了
They dreamt of the day when the Dwarves of Erebor would reclaim their homeland.
他们无时无刻都在想着矮人能重夺自己的故乡
There is no choice, Balin.
没有其他选择 巴林
Not for me.
我别无选择
Then we are with you, laddie.
那么 我们将与你同生共死
We will see it done.
我们会成功的
# Far over the misty mountains cold #
# 登上远山冰寒之巅 #
# To dungeons deep #
# 深入地牢深渊之底 #
# And caverns old #
# 探索古老洞窟之中 #
# We must away #
# 在太阳升起之前 #
# 'Ere break of day #
# 我们必须整装出发 #
# To find our long-forgotten gold #
# 去追寻那遗落之财 #
# The pines were roaring on the height #
# 高处的松树在低吼 #
# The winds were moaning in the night #
# 夜晚的寒风在呼啸 #
# The fire was red, it flaming spread #
# 希望之火 传播不息 #
# The trees like torches blazed with light #
# 光明从这火中而来 #
Hello?
早啊?
Yes.
好样的
Here, Mr. Bilbo, where are you off to?
比尔博先生 你这是去哪儿?
- Can't stop, I'm already late!  - Late for what?
- 不能停下说 我已经迟到了!  - 什么迟到?
I'm going on an adventure!
我要去冒险!
I said it. Didn't I say it? Coming here was a waste of time.
我说过的 我说过吗? 这一趟来得不值啊
That's true enough.
你说的没错
Ridiculous notion. Use a Hobbit? A Halfling?
这主意太荒唐了 霍比特人? 半身人(通用语中对霍比特人的称呼)?
Wait!
等等!
I signed it.
我签名了
Here.
给
Everything appears to be in order.
很好 一切都按程序填写
Welcome, Master Baggins...
欢迎 巴金斯大师...
to the company of Thorin Oakenshield.
欢迎加入索林・橡木盾小队
Give him a pony.
给他一匹马崽子
No, no, that won't be necessary.
哦 不用这么麻烦了
Thank you. I'm sure I can keep up on foot.
谢了 我自信我能赶上你们步伐
I've done my fair share of walking holidays, you know?
我经常出去徒步旅游的 知道吗?
Even got as far as Frogmorton once.
有一次还跑到蛙村去了
Come on, Nori. Pay up.
快点 诺力 给钱
- One more.  - Thanks, lad.
- 还有一袋  - 谢了 小子
What's that about?
这是干嘛?
Oh, they took wagers on whether or not you'd turn up.
哦 他们在打赌 赌你会不会回心转意
Most of them bet that you wouldn't.
大多数人赌你不会
And what did you think?
你觉得呢?
My dear fellow, I never doubted you for a second.
我的好朋友 我从未怀疑过你
It's horse hair. Having a reaction.
这马毛让我过敏了
No, wait, wait, stop.
不不 等下
Stop! We have to turn around.
停下! 我们得回头
What on earth is the matter?
到底怎么啦?
- I forgot my handkerchief.  - Here.
- 我忘记带我的手帕了  - 给你
Use this.
用这个
Move on.
继续行进
You'll have to manage without pocket handkerchiefs...
你得习惯不带手帕的生活...
and a good many other things, Bilbo Baggins...
还有很多其他的事情 比尔博・巴金斯...
before we reach our journey's end.
直到这趟旅程结束
You were born to the rolling hills and little rivers of the Shire.
你在夏尔的丘陵与小河边长大
But home is now behind you.
但如今家园已在身后
The world is ahead.
世界尽在眼前
Hello, girl. Who's a good girl?
嗨 姑娘 真是个好姑娘!
It's our little secret, Myrtle.
这是我俩的小秘密 桃金娘
You must tell no one. Shh, shh.
谁也不许告诉 嘘 嘘
What was that?
那是什么?
Orcs.
是半兽人
Orcs?
半兽人?
Throat-cutters. There'll be dozens of them out there.
是些嗜杀成性的家伙 外头起码有几十个
The lone-lands are crawling with them.
在孤土到处可见它们的身影(孤土西起蓝山 东至迷雾山脉)
They strike in the wee small hours when everyone's asleep.
他们总在凌晨时分 人们熟睡时动手
Quick and quiet, no screams. Just lots of blood.
干脆利落 人们来不及尖叫 就已血流成河
You think that's funny?
你们以为这些很好玩?
You think a night raid by Orcs is a joke?
你们以为被半兽人夜袭是个玩笑?
We didn't mean anything by it.
我们不是这个意思
No, you didn't.
是啊 你们不是这个意思
You know nothing of the world.
你们对这世界根本一无所知
Don't mind him, laddie.
别介意 小家伙
Thorin has more cause than most to hate Orcs.
索林比任何人都更有理由痛恨半兽人
After the dragon took the Lonely Mountain...
在恶龙占领孤山后...
King Thror tried to reclaim the ancient Dwarf kingdom of Moria.
国王索尔曾试图收复古老的矮人王国 摩瑞亚
But our enemy had got there first.
但敌人早已捷足先登
Moria had been taken by legions of Orcs...
摩瑞亚被半兽人军团占领...
led by the most vile of all their race:
领头的是它们族群中最邪恶的家伙
Azog the Defiler.
毁灭者阿索格
The giant Gundabad Orc...
这个身形巨大的刚达巴半兽人
had sworn to wipe out the line of Durin.
曾发誓要杀尽杜林一族
He began...
他一出手...
by beheading the king.
就砍下了国王的脑袋
No!
不!
Thrain, Thorin's father, was driven mad by grief.
索林的父亲索恩悲伤得几乎发狂
He went missing. Taken prisoner or killed...
他失踪了 也许被俘 也许被杀...
We did not know.
我们无从知晓
We were leaderless.
我们失去了首领
Defeat and death...
失败与死亡...
were upon us.
正步步紧逼
That is when I saw him.
就在那时我看到了他
A young Dwarf prince...
一位年轻的矮人王子...
facing down the pale Orc.
力战苍白半兽人
He stood alone against this terrible foe.
他孤身与强敌血战
His armor rent...
他的盔甲碎了...
wielding nothing but an oaken branch as a shield.
只能挥舞着一截橡木当盾牌
Azog the Defiler learned that day...
那一天 毁灭者阿索格明白了...
that the line of Durin would not be so easily broken.
杜林族系绝不会轻易瓦解
Our forces rallied...
我们集结了军力
and drove the Orcs back.
击退了半兽人
And our enemy...
我们的敌人...
had been defeated.
被打败了
But there was no feast...
但那一晚既没有庆宴...
nor song that night...
也没有歌声...
for our dead were beyond the count of grief.
因为我们的伤亡太过惨重
We few had survived.
只有极少数得以存活
And I thought to myself then...
于是我告诉自己...
there is one who I could follow.
还有这样一个人值得我去追随
There is one...
还有这样一个人...
I could call king.
我愿视为王
And the pale Orc?
那苍白半兽人呢?
What happened to him?
他后来怎么样了?
He slunk back into the hole whence he came.
他溜回了起兵的那个洞里
That filth died of his wounds long ago.
早就因伤势过重死了
Here, Mr. Gandalf, can't you do something about this deluge?
喂 甘道夫先生 这水漫金山的你就不能想想办法吗?
It is raining, Master Dwarf...
这是在下雨 矮人大人...
and it will continue to rain until the rain is done.
想止住雨的唯一办法就是等雨自己停下来
If you wish to change the weather of the world, you should find yourself another Wizard.
如果你想改变这世界上的天气 那恐怕得找别的巫师了
- Are there any?  - What?
- 有别的吗?  - 别的什么?
- Other Wizards.  - There are five of us.
- 别的巫师  - 像我们这样的人有五个
The greatest of our order is Saruman the White.
其中最位高权重的是白袍萨鲁曼
Then there are the two Blue Wizards...
接下来是两位蓝袍巫师...
Do you know, I've quite forgotten their names.
不过我已经忘了他们的名字了
And who is the fifth?
那第五个呢?
Well, that would be Radagast the Brown.
是褐袍瑞达加斯特
Is he a great Wizard? Or is he more like you?
他是个厉害的巫师吗? 还是和你差不多的?
I think he's a very great Wizard, in his own way.
我想他自有他厉害的地方
He's a gentle soul who prefers the company of animals to others.
他心地温和 偏爱与动物为伴
He keeps a watchful eye over the vast forest lands...
始终盯防着东部的...
to the east. And a good thing too.
广阔森林地带 这是件好事
For always evil will look to find a foothold in this world.
因为邪恶势力总会试图在世上寻找立足之地
Not good. Not good at all.
不妙 大事不妙了
Eww.
唷
Oh, no. Sebastian.
哦 不 塞巴斯蒂安
Good gracious.
我的天哪
Come on.
快点
Move back! Give him some air, for goodness sake.
退后! 给它点新鲜空气 拜托了
There. There.
来 给
I don't understand why it's not working.
我不明白为什么不起作用
It's not as if it's witchcraft.
这又不是巫术
Witchcraft.
巫术
Oh, but it is.
哦 但它确实是巫术
A dark and powerful magic.
一种邪恶 强大的魔法
Lerya laman naiquentallo.
让这动物免于诅咒
Si a hlare omaquettar.
现在聆听我的声音
Na coilerya en-vinyanta.
让其重新焕发生机
Where on this good earth did those foul creatures come from?
那些肮脏的生物究竟是从哪里来的?
The old fortress?
古要塞?
Show me.
带我去
We'll camp here for the night.
我们今晚在这里扎营
Fili, Kili, look after the ponies. Make sure you stay with them.
菲力 奇力 照看好马儿 和它们待在一块
A farmer and his family used to live here.
这里以前住着一户农民
- Oin, Gloin. Get a fire going.  - Aye.
- 欧因 葛罗因 生火  - 是
Right you are.
好的
I think it would be wiser to move on.
我觉得还是继续前进比较明智
We could make for the Hidden Valley.
我们可以前往幽谷
I have told you already...
我已经告诉你了...
I will not go near that place.
我不会靠近那地方
Why not? The Elves could help us.
为什么? 精灵可以提供帮助
We could get food, rest, advice.
我们能补充食物 休养生息 听取建议
I do not need their advice.
我不需要精灵的建议
We have a map that we cannot read. Lord Elrond could help us.
我们还有一张地图看不懂 爱隆能帮助我们
Help?
帮助?
A dragon attacks Erebor.
恶龙袭击伊鲁柏的时候
What help came from the Elves?
精灵提供帮助了吗?
Orcs plunder Moria...
半兽人扫荡摩瑞亚...
desecrate our sacred halls.
亵渎圣殿的时候
The Elves looked on and did nothing.
精灵们只是袖手旁观
And you ask me to seek out the very people who betrayed my grandfather.
而你却要我去找那些背叛我祖父的人
Who betrayed my father.
那些背叛我父亲的人
You are neither of them.
但你不是他们
I did not give you that map and key for you to hold onto the past.
我给你地图和钥匙 不是为了让你执着于往事
I did not know that they were yours to keep.
那本来就是属于我的
Everything all right? Gandalf, where are you going?
没事吧? 甘道夫你要去哪?
To seek the company of the only one around here who's got any sense.
去找这里唯一一个有理智的人
- And who's that?  - Myself, Mr. Baggins.
- 是谁?  - 我自己 巴金斯先生
I've had enough of Dwarves for one day.
我今天已经受够了矮人了
Come on, Bombur, we're hungry.
快点 庞博 我们都饿了
Is he coming back?
他会回来吗?
He's been a long time.
他已经离开很久了
- Who?  - Gandalf.
- 谁?  - 甘道夫
He's a Wizard. He does as he chooses.
他是个巫师 知道自己在做什么
Here, do us a favor. Take this to the lads.
拿着 帮个忙 把这个给小伙子们送去
Stop it. You've had plenty.
住手 你已经吃得够多了
Aye, it's not a bad stew, Bombur. I've had worse.
饭做得不错啊 庞博 我还吃过更糟的
- Dori could've cooked it.  - Ha-ha-ha.
- 本来可以让朵力做的  - 哈哈哈
Hilarious.
太好笑了
What's the matter?
怎么了?
- We're supposed to be looking after the ponies.  - Only we've encountered a slight problem.
- 我们本应该看着马的  - 但我们遇到了些小问题
We had 16.
原本有16匹马
Now there's 14.
现在只有14匹了
Daisy and Bungo are missing.
黛西和伯格不见了
Well, that's not good. Ha, ha.
哦 那可不妙 哈 哈
And that is not good at all. Shouldn't we tell Thorin?
那可糟透了 要去告诉索林吗?
Uh, no. Let's not worry him.
呃 不要 别让他担心
As our official burglar, we thought you might like to look into it.
身为队伍的正式飞贼 我们觉得你也许愿意去调查一下
Well, uh...
这个 呃...
- Look, something big uprooted these trees.  - That was our thinking.
- 瞧 树像是被什么大家伙连根拔起的  - 我们也是这么想的
It's something very big and possibly quite dangerous.
应该是某种巨大且危险的东西
Hey.
嘿
There's a light.
那里有光亮
Over here.
过来
Stay down.
蹲下
What is it?
那是什么?
Trolls.
食人妖
Oh.
哦
He's got Myrtle and Minty.
他又抓走了桃金娘和薄荷
I think they're gonna eat them. We have to do something.
我想它们会被吃掉的 我们得采取行动
Yes, you should.
没错 你快上吧
Mountain Trolls are slow and stupid, and you're so small, they'll never see you.
食人妖脑袋又笨 动作又慢 你这么小 他们根本看不到你
It's perfectly safe. We'll be behind you.
绝对安全 我们会跟在你身后的
If you run into trouble, hoot twice like a barn owl and once like a brown owl.
如果遇到麻烦 就学谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 棕色猫头鹰叫一声
Twice like a barn owl. No, twice like a brown... Once like a...
谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 不对 棕色猫头鹰叫两... 谷仓...
Like a... Are you sure this is a good idea?
叫... 你们确定这是个好主意吗?
Mutton yesterday, mutton today...
昨天吃羊肉 今天吃羊肉...
and, blimey, if it don't look like mutton again tomorrow.
天哪 不会明天也吃羊肉吧
Quit your griping.
别发牢骚了
These ain't sheep. These is fresh nags.
这不是羊 这是新鲜的马肉
Oh! I don't like horse. I never have. Not enough fat on them.
哦! 我不喜欢马 从来没喜欢过 它们身上连肥肉都没有
Well, it's better than leathery old farmer.
总比干巴巴的老农夫好吧
All skin and bone, he was. I'm still picking bits of him out of me teeth.
他简直是皮包骨头 到现在我牙缝里还有呢
Well, that's lovely, that is. A floater.
真棒 瞧你干的好事 鼻涕进锅里了
Might improve the flavor.
没准能添点味儿
Ah. There's more where that came from.
啊 这儿还有呢
- Oh, no, you don't!  - Ow!
- 哦 不 不准这样!  - 噢!
Sit down!
坐下!
Well, I hope you're gonna gut these nags.
希望你能把这些马的内脏去掉
I don't like the stinky parts.
我不喜欢吃内脏
- Ow!  - I said sit down.
- 噢!  - 我说了 坐下
I'm starving!
我饿死了!
Now, are we having horse tonight or what?
今晚到底吃不吃马肉了?
Shut your cakehole. You'll eat what I give you.
闭上你的臭嘴 我给什么你就吃什么
How come he's the cook? Everything tastes the same.
怎么让他当厨师的? 所有东西尝起来都是一个味儿
Everything tastes like chicken.
所有东西吃着都像鸡肉
Except the chicken.
除了鸡肉不像
What tastes like fish!
鸡肉倒像是鱼!
I'm just saying, a little appreciation would be nice.
我刚说过 你们应该心存感激
Oh. "Thank you very much, Bert. Lovely stew, Bert."
哦 "谢谢你 伯特 做得真棒 伯特"
- How hard is that?  - Shh. Shh, shh. Shh.
- 这有什么难的?  - 嘘 嘘
Just needs a sprinkle of squirrel dung.
只需要再撒些松鼠粪
Here, that's my grog.
嘿 那是我的酒
Sorry. Ow!
抱歉 噢!
Ooh. That is beautifully balanced, that is.
哦 味道正好 不错
Wrap your laughing gear around that, eh?
把你嘴巴凑过来接住 嗯?
Good, isn't it?
不错吧?
That's why I'm the cook.
所以要我来当厨师
Oh, my guts are grumbling. I got to snaffle something.
哦 我肚子都叫了 我需要捞点东西吃
- Flesh, I need flesh.  - Ah! Ah!
- 肉 我要肉  - 啊! 啊!
Blimey!
天哪!
Bert. Bert! Look what's come out of me hooter.
伯特 伯特! 看我鼻子里喷出了什么
It's got arms and legs and everything.
它有手有脚 什么都有
What is it?
这是什么东西?
I don't know. But I don't like the way it wriggles around.
我不知道 但我不喜欢它扭来扭去的样子
What are you, then? An oversized squirrel?
你是什么东西? 特大号松鼠吗?
I'm a burglar... Uh, Hobbit.
我是个飞... 呃 霍比特人
A burglar Hobbit?
一个飞蛾霍比特人?
Can we cook him?
我们能煮了他吗?
We can try.
可以试试
He wouldn't make more than a mouthful.
他还不够我咬一大口的
Not when he's skinned and boned.
尽管不是皮包骨头
Perhaps there's more burglar Hobbits around these parts.
也许附近还有更多的飞蛾霍比特人
Might be enough for a pie.
说不定够做个派
- Grab him!  - He's too quick.
- 抓住他!  - 他动作太快了
Right. Come here, you little...
好吧 快过来 你这小东...
Gotcha.
抓住你了
Are there any more of you little fellas hiding where you shouldn't?
你还有其他小同伴躲在不该躲的地方吗?
No.
没有
He's lying.
他在撒谎
- No, I'm not!  - Hold his toes over the fire.
- 不 我没有!  - 把他悬到火上烤
Make him squeal!
让他尖叫!
Drop him!
把他放下!
You what?
你说什么?
I said...
我说...
drop him.
把他放下
Get the sacks! Stick them in the sacks!
拿袋子来! 把他们用麻袋套上!
Ow!
噢!
Come on! Get up!
快点! 起来!
- Bilbo!  - Don't!
- 比尔博!  - 不要!
Lay down your arms...
放下武器...
or we'll rip his off.
不然我们就撕了他
Oh! That's hot, that's hot, that's hot!
哦! 烫死了 烫死了 烫死了!
Don't bother cooking them.
别费劲煮他们了
Let's just sit on them and squash them into jelly.
我们直接坐上去 把他们压成肉酱吧
They should be sauteed and grilled with a sprinkle of sage.
应该先这样爆炒再煎烤 最后撒些鼠尾草
Is this really necessary?
这真的有必要吗?
That does sound quite nice.
听起来确实不错
- Untie me, mister.  - Eat someone your own size.
- 松开我 先生  - 去吃和你个子一样大的东西吧
Never mind the seasoning.
别介意调料了
We ain't got all night.
我们没有一整晚的时间
Dawn ain't far away. Let's get a move on.
黎明不远了 我们动作快点
I don't fancy being turned to stone.
我可不想被变成石头
Wait!
等等!
You are making a terrible mistake.
你们犯了个大错
You can't reason with them. They're half-wits!
你没法和他们讲道理 他们是白痴!
Half-wits? What does that make us?
白痴? 那我们成什么了?
I meant with the seasoning.
我指的是调料的事
What about the seasoning?
调料怎么了?
Well, have you smelt them?
你闻过他们的味道了么?
You're gonna need something stronger than sage before you plate this lot up.
想把他们烤熟装盘 你就得用比鼠尾草味道更重的调料
- Traitor!  - What do you know about cooking Dwarf?
- 叛徒!  - 你懂怎么煮矮人?
Shut up.
闭嘴
Let the flurgaburburhobbit talk.
让 小格灰灰霍比特人来说
The secret to cooking Dwarf is...
煮矮人的秘诀就在于...
- Yes? Come on. Tell us the secret.  - It's, uh...
- 嗯? 说吧 告诉我们秘诀  - 呃 就是...
Yes, I'm telling you. The secret is...
我正准备说呢 秘诀就是...
to skin them first.
先剥皮
What? Skin us?
什么? 剥我们的皮?
Tom, get me filleting knife.
汤姆 给我拿切片刀来
I'll skin you, you little...!
我要剥了你的皮! 你这小...
I won't forget that. I won't forget it.
我不会忘记这件事的 我绝不会忘记
What a load of rubbish.
都是废话
I've eaten plenty with their skins on.
我吃过好多带皮的
Scarf them, I say, boots and all.
一口吞下 连靴子也吃下去
He's right.
他说的对
Nothing wrong with a bit of raw Dwarf.
吃些活矮人也没关系
Nice and crunchy.
美味又松脆
Oh, not that one. He's infected.
不 别挑那个 他被感染了
- Huh?  - You what?
- 嗯?  - 你说什么?
Yeah, he's got worms in his tubes.
没错 他肠道里有虫子
- Eww!  - Aah!
- 呕!  - 啊!
In fact, they all have. They're infested with parasites.
事实上 他们都被感染了 他们体内长满了寄生虫
It's a terrible business. I wouldn't risk it. I really wouldn't.
那真是太可怕了 我可不会冒这种险 绝对不会
Parasites? Did he say "parasites"?
寄生虫? 他说了 "寄生虫" ?
We don't have parasites. You have parasites!
我们没有寄生虫 你才有寄生虫呢!
What are you talking about, laddie?
你在说什么呢 小伙子?
I've got parasites as big as my arm.
我的寄生虫和手臂一样粗
Mine are the biggest parasites. I've got huge parasites.
我的寄生虫最大了 超大号寄生虫
- We're riddled.  - Yes, I'm riddled.
- 我们身上到处都是  - 没错 我全身都是
Yes, we are, badly.
是的 我们糟透了
What would you have us do, then?
那么你要我们怎么办?
Let them all go?
放他们走?
- Well...  - You think I don't know what you're up to?
- 这个...  - 你以为我不知道你想干什么?
This little ferret is taking us for fools.
这只小耗子把我们当傻子耍呢
- Ferret?  - Fools?
- 耗子?  - 傻子?
The dawn will take you all.
曙光将把你们全部消灭
- Who's that?  - No idea.
- 那是谁?  - 不知道
Can we eat him too?
我们能把他也吃了吗?
Get your foot out of my back.
把你的脚从我背上拿开
Ah.
啊
Where did you go to, if I may ask?
容我问一句 你之前去哪里了?
To look ahead.
去前面看看
- What brought you back?  - Looking behind.
- 你为什么又回来了?  - 看看后面
Nasty business.
真糟糕
Still, they're all in one piece.
幸好 大家都没事
No thanks to your burglar.
你的飞贼可没什么功劳
He had the nous to play for time.
他给你们争取了时间
None of the rest of you thought of that.
你们都没有意识到这点
They must have come down from the Ettenmoors.
这些食人妖一定都是从伊顿荒原来的
Since when do Mountain Trolls venture this far south?
从什么时候开始 他们会往南走得这么远?
Ooh. Not for an age.
哦 没多久
Not since a darker power ruled these lands.
就在黑暗势力统治这片土地之后
They could not have moved in daylight.
他们不能在白天活动
There must be a cave nearby.
这附近一定会有个洞穴
Oh, what's that stench?
哦 这股臭味是哪来的?
It's a Troll-hoard.
这里是食人妖的巢穴
Be careful what you touch.
小心你们摸到的东西
Seems a shame just to leave it lying around.
把财宝随意扔放 好像太可惜了
- Anyone could take it.  - Agreed.
- 谁都可以拿走  - 同意
- Nori.  - Yeah?
- 诺力  - 干什么?
Get a shovel.
拿把铲子来
These swords were not made by any Troll.
这些剑不是食人妖做的
Nor were they made by any smith among men.
也不是人类铁匠做的
These were forged in Gondolin...
这些是第一纪的高等精灵...
by the High Elves of the First Age.
在贡多林锻造的
You could not wish for a finer blade.
没有比这更锋利的刀刃了
- Set it down.  - That's good.
- 把它埋起来  - 太好了
All right, come on. Quick.
好了 继续 快点
We're making a long-term deposit.
我们也存点长期储蓄
Let's get out of this foul place.
我们快离开这个臭烘烘的地方吧
Come on, let's go.
走吧 我们走
Bofur, Gloin, Nori.
跟上 波佛 葛罗因 诺力
- Bilbo.  - Hmm?
- 比尔博  - 嗯?
Here.
给你
This is about your size.
这个尺寸正适合你
I can't take this.
我不能接受它
The blade is of Elvish make...
这把剑是精灵制作的...
which means it will glow blue when Orcs or Goblins are nearby.
也就是说当半兽人或哥布林靠近的时候 它会发出蓝色的光
I have never used a sword in my life.
我这辈子都没用过剑
And I hope you never have to.
我希望你永远用不上它
But if you do, remember this:
但是如果你用到了 要记住
True courage is about knowing not when to take a life...
真正的勇气 不是体现在杀戮的时候...
but when to spare one.
而是宽恕的时候
Something's coming!
有什么东西过来了!
- Gandalf.  - Stay together!
- 甘道夫  - 聚在一起!
Hurry now! Arm yourselves!
快点! 拿上武器!
Thieves! Fire! Murder!
小偷! 大火! 谋杀!
Radagast.
瑞达加斯特
It's Radagast the Brown.
这是褐袍瑞达加斯特
Well...
那么...
What on earth are you doing here?
你来这里到底要干什么?
I was looking for you, Gandalf.
我在找你 甘道夫
Something's wrong.
出事了
Something's terribly wrong.
出大事了
Yes?
怎么了?
Oh.
哦
Just give me a minute.
稍等一下
Oh. I had a thought and now I've lost it.
哦 我有件事想说 但是我给忘了
It was right there...
它就在...
on the tip of my tongue.
我的舌尖上
Oh.
哦
It's not a thought at all.
它根本不是一件事
It's a silly old...
它是一只笨笨的...
stick insect.
老竹节虫
The Greenwood is sick, Gandalf.
巨绿森林生病了 甘道夫
A darkness has fallen over it.
黑暗已经将它笼罩
Nothing grows anymore.
万物都不再生长
At least, nothing good.
至少 美好的东西都不再生长
The air is foul with decay.
空气中弥漫着浑浊的腐臭
But worse are the webs.
更糟糕的是蛛网
Webs? What do you mean?
蛛网? 什么意思?
Spiders, Gandalf.
蜘蛛 甘道夫
Giant ones.
巨型的蜘蛛
Some kind of spawn of Ungoliant, or I am not a Wizard.
我肯定是昂哥立安的后代 否则我就不是个巫师
I followed their trail.
我沿着它们的踪迹
They came from Dol Guldur.
追踪到它们来自多尔戈多
Huh?
啊?
Dol Guldur?
来自多尔戈多?
But the old fortress is abandoned.
但是那座古老的堡垒已经被废弃了
No, Gandalf.
不 甘道夫
It's not.
那里有人
A dark power dwells in there...
一股黑暗势力盘踞在那里...
Such as I have never...
那是我从未感受过的...
felt before.
黑暗
It is The Shadow of an ancient horror.
那是远古魔影
One that can summon the spirits...
它可以召唤...
of the dead.
亡者之灵
I saw him, Gandalf.
我看到他了 甘道夫
From out of the darkness...
从黑暗中...
a Necromancer...
走出来的是...
has come.
一位
Radagast.
死灵法师
Quick! Quick, quick! Quick, quick!
快! 快! 快点! 快点!
Wait for me!
等等我!
Sorry.
对不起
Try a little Old Toby.
来一口老托比吧
It'll help settle your nerves.
它能帮你放松下来
And out.
吐出来
Now...
现在好好想想...
a Necromancer. Are you sure?
你确定那是死灵法师吗?
That is not...
那可不是...
from the world of the living.
来自我们这个世界的东西
Was that a wolf? Are there wolves out there?
那是狼吗? 这附近有狼吗?
Wolves? No, that is not a wolf.
狼? 不 那不是一般的狼
Kili! Get your bow!
奇力! 射箭!
Warg scouts.
前锋座狼
Which means an Orc pack is not far behind.
这说明半兽人的队伍已经不远了
Orc pack?
半兽人的队伍?
Who did you tell about your quest...
除了你的族人之外...
beyond your kin?
你还把这次探险的事告诉谁了?
No one.
谁都没有
Who did you tell?
你到底告诉谁了?
No one, I swear.
没有 我发誓
What in...
以杜林之名...
Durin's name is going on?
告诉我出了什么麻烦?
You are being hunted.
你们掉进陷阱了
We have to get out of here.
我们得离开这里
We can't. We have no ponies.
我们没法离开 我们没有小马了
They bolted.
它们跑散了
I'll draw them off.
我去引开他们
These are Gundabad Wargs.
他们是刚达巴的座狼
They will outrun you.
你跑不过他们的
These are Rhosgobel rabbits.
这些是罗斯加堡的兔子
I'd like to see them try.
我倒想让它们比试比试
Come on! Come on!
来啊! 来啊!
Come and get me! Ha, ha!
来抓我啊! 哈哈!
Come on.
过来
Stay together.
别走散了
Move!
快跑!
Ori, no! Get back.
欧力 停! 回来
All of you, come on. Quick!
所有人 过来 快!
Where are you leading us?
你要带我们去哪?
Move!
快跑!
Run!
快!
There they are!
他们在那里!
This way!
这边走!
Quickly!
快点!
There's more coming!
来的越来越多了!
Kili!
奇力!
Shoot them!
射箭!
We're surrounded!
我们被包围了!
Where's Gandalf?
甘道夫在哪里?
He's abandoned us.
他抛弃了我们
Hold your ground!
稳住阵脚!
This way, you fools!
来这边 你们这些傻瓜!
Come on, move!
过来 快!
Quickly!
快点!
All of you!
大家都来这里!
Come on!
过来!
Go, go, go!
快 快 快!
Eight, nine, ten.
八 九 十
Kili!
快点! 奇力!
Run!
快过来!
Elves.
是精灵
I cannot see...
我看不出来...
where the pathway leads. Do we follow it or no?
这条路通向哪里 我们走不走?
Follow it, of course.
当然要走
I think that would be wise.
明智的选择
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Where are we?
我们这是在哪?
You can feel it?
你有感觉?
Yes. It feels like...
是啊 感觉就像是...
Well, like magic.
像是有魔法一样
That's exactly what it is.
那就对了
A very powerful magic.
这是非常强大的魔法
There's light ahead.
前面有光
The Valley of Imladris.
这是伊姆拉崔河谷
In the common tongue, it's known by another name.
更多的时候 它有另一个名字
Rivendell.
瑞文戴尔
Here lies the Last Homely House East of the Sea.
这里是大海东岸最后的美丽家园
This was your plan all along.
这都是你计划好的
To seek refuge with our enemy.
向我们的敌人寻求帮助
You have no enemies here, Thorin Oakenshield.
这里没有你的敌人 索林・橡木盾
The only ill will to be found...
如果你在林谷里...
in this valley is that which you bring yourself.
感到任何敌意 那也是你自己身上的
You think the Elves will give our quest their blessing?
你以为精灵会为我们的探险祝福吗?
They will try to stop us.
他们会阻止我们
Of course they will. But we have questions that need to be answered.
没错 但是我们也有疑问需要他们指点
If we are to be successful, this will need to be handled with tact.
所以如果我们想成功 和精灵的接触就需要机智
And respect.
和尊重
And no small degree of charm.
以及一定的风度
Which is why you will leave the talking to me.
所以待会儿的谈判 就交给我吧
Mithrandir.
米斯兰迪尔
Ah.
啊
Lindir.
林迪尔
Stay sharp.
注意点
I must speak with Lord Elrond.
我有事得和爱隆谈谈
My Lord Elrond is not here.
爱隆殿下不在这里
Not here?
不在这里?
Where is he?
他在哪?
Close ranks!
靠紧!
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Lord Elrond.
爱隆
Strange for Orcs to come so close to our borders.
这很奇怪 半兽人离我们的边界这么近
Something or someone has drawn them near.
是什么人或者什么事引他们过来的
Ah. That may have been us.
啊 那大概是我们
Welcome, Thorin, son of Thrain.
欢迎你 索恩之子索林
I do not believe we have met.
我想我们没见过
You have your grandfather's bearing.
你有你祖父的风范
I knew Thror when he ruled...
索尔统治山脉的时候...
- Under the Mountain.  - Indeed? He made no mention of you.
- 我认识他  - 真的? 他从没提起过你
Nartho i noer, toltho i viruvor. Boe i annam vann a nethail vin.
生起炉火 盛上美酒 我们得款待我们的客人(辛达语)
What is he saying?
他在说什么?
Does he offer us insult?
他是在侮辱我们吗?
No, Master Gloin, he's offering you food.
不 葛罗因 他要为你们提供食物
Well...
好吧...
in that case, lead on.
这样的话 带路吧
Hey. Come on.
嘿 来吧
Try it. Just a mouthful.
试试嘛 就吃一口
I don't like green food.
我不喜欢绿叶菜
Where's the meat?
肉在哪里?
Have they got any chips?
他们这里有薯片吗?
Kind of you...
感谢你...
to invite us.
招待我们
Not really dressed for dinner.
我都没穿正式的服装
Well, you never are.
你从来都没穿过
I can't say I fancy Elf maids myself, too thin.
我个人感觉不是太喜欢女精灵 她们太瘦了
They're all high cheekbones...
她们都有高高的颧骨...
and creamy skin.
和雪白的皮肤
Not enough facial hair for me.
我觉得她们的头发也不够浓密
Although that one there is not bad.
不过那边的那个还不错
That's not an Elf maid.
那不是个女精灵
That's funny.
有点意思
This is Orcrist, the Goblin-cleaver.
这是奥格瑞斯特 哥布林斩杀者
A famous blade...
是由我的同族...
forged by the High Elves of the West, my kin.
西方高等精灵锻造的著名的宝剑
May it serve you well.
愿它能够帮助你
And this...
这是...
is Glamdring...
格兰瑞...
the Foehammer. Sword...
敌击剑 这是...
of the King of Gondolin.
贡多林之王的宝剑
These were made for the Goblin Wars of the First Age.
这些是为第一纪元的哥布林大战铸造的
I wouldn't bother, laddie.
我没有冒犯的意思 年轻人
Swords are named for the great deeds they do in war.
宝剑是以它在战争中的功勋命名的
What are you saying, my sword hasn't seen battle?
你什么意思 我的剑没有经历过战争?
I'm not actually sure it is a sword.
我都不确定它是一把剑
More of a letter opener, really.
它更像是一把拆信刀 真的
- How did you come by these?  - We found them...
- 你是怎么得到这些的?  - 我们是在...
in a Troll-hoard on the Great East Road...
东方大道上的一个食人妖巢穴找到的...
shortly before...
就在...
- we were ambushed by Orcs.  - And what were you doing...
- 我们被半兽人攻击之前  - 你们在...
on the Great East Road?
东方大道上干什么?
Excuse me.
不好意思
Thirteen Dwarves...
十三个矮人...
and a Halfling. Hm.
和一个半身人
Strange traveling companions, Gandalf.
真是奇怪的旅行伙伴啊 甘道夫
These are the descendants of the house of Durin.
他们都是杜林矮人的后代
They're noble, decent folk.
他们出身贵族 行事得体
And they're surprisingly cultured.
而且都非常有教养
They've got a deep love...
他们都非常...
- of the arts.  - Change the tune, why don't you?
- 热爱艺术  - 换首曲子 行不行?
I feel like I'm at a funeral.
我感觉像是在参加葬礼
- Did somebody die?  - All right...
- 有人死了吗?  - 好吧...
lads. There's only one thing for it.
伙计们 看我的
# There's #
# 在 #
# An #
# 古老的灰山脚下 #
# Inn, there's an inn There's a merry old inn #
# 有一个小旅馆 #
# Beneath an old gray hill #
# 老旧又欢乐的旅馆 #
# And there they brew a beer so brown The man in the moon #
# 那里的人会酿棕色的啤酒 #
# Himself came down one night #
# 某个夜晚 月中人来到人间 #
# To drink his fill #
# 在那里痛饮尽欢 #
# Oh #
# 哦 #
# The ostler has a tipsy cat #
# 马夫的猫醉醺醺 #
# That played a five-stringed fiddle #
# 它还会弹五弦琴 #
# And up and down he saws his bow #
# 马夫来来回回锯木头 #
# Now squeaking high #
# 声音时而低 #
# Now purring low #
# 时而高 #
# Now sawing in the middle #
# 有时不低也不高 #
# So #
# 也就是说 #
# The cat on the fiddle #
# 小提琴上有只猫 #
# Played hey-diddle-diddle A drink that'll wake the dead #
# 弹奏古怪的歌谣 那酒有起死回生的功效 #
# He squeaked and he sawed And he quickened #
# 他锯木头发出吱吱的声音 他欢乐得不得了 #
# The tune and the landlord #
# 旅馆老板和小调 #
# Shook the man #
# 下了他一大跳 #
# In the Moon "It's after #
# 回到月亮上 他才说道 #
# Three!" he said #
# "已经凌晨三点了" #
Our business is no concern of Elves.
我们的事和精灵无关
For goodness sake, Thorin...
看在上帝的份上 索林...
- show him the map.  - It is the legacy...
- 给他看看地图  - 地图是...
of my people.
我祖先的遗物
It is mine to protect, as are its secrets.
我需要保护它 以及它所承载的秘密
Save me from the stubbornness of Dwarves.
你们矮人不要那么固执好吗
Your pride will be your downfall.
你的骄傲会给你带来麻烦
You stand in the presence of one of the few in Middle-earth...
站在你面前的是在中土世界仅有的几个...
who can read that map. Show it to Lord Elrond.
能看懂地图的人 把地图给爱隆
Thorin, no.
索林 不行
Erebor.
是伊鲁柏
What is your interest...
你们为什么...
in this map?
对这张地图感兴趣?
It's mainly academic.
主要是学术方面的原因
As you know...
你知道...
this sort of artifact sometimes contains hidden text.
这样的文物上有时会带有隐含的信息
You still read ancient Dwarvish, do you not?
你还能看懂古矮人文 不是吗?
Cirth Ithil
是色斯文(一种基于月相变化的文字)
Moon runes?
月亮文字?
Of course.
原来如此
An easy thing to miss.
这是很容易被忽视的密码
Well, in this case, that is true.
确实如此
Moon runes can only be read by the light of a moon...
要解读月亮文字 必须有和写下密码那天...
of the same shape and season...
同样季节...
as the day on which they were written.
同样月相的月光
Can you read them?
你能读懂它们吗?
These runes were written on a Midsummer's Eve...
这些文字是在仲夏夜写的...
by the light of a crescent moon nearly 200 years ago.
在两百年前一弯新月的月光下
It would seem you were meant to come to Rivendell.
看起来你们注定要来到此地
Fate is with you...
这是你们的命运...
Thorin Oakenshield. The same moon...
索林・橡木盾 今晚...
shines upon us tonight.
同样的月光正在照耀着我们
"Stand by the...
"画眉鸟...
gray stone when the thrush knocks...
敲击之时 站在灰色石头旁...
and the setting sun with the last light of Durin's Day...
杜林日的最后一抹阳光...
- will shine upon the keyhole. "  - Durin's Day?
- 将会落在锁眼上"  - 杜林日?
It is the start of the Dwarves' new year, when the last moon of autumn...
那是矮人的新年 当秋季最后的月光...
and the first sun of winter appear in the sky together.
和冬天第一缕阳光同时出现在天空的时候
This is ill news.
这是个坏消息
Summer is passing. Durin's Day will soon be upon us.
夏天就要过去 杜林日马上就要到了
We still have time.
我们还有时间
- Time? For what?  - To find the entrance.
- 时间? 干什么?  - 找到入口
We have to be standing in exactly the right spot at exactly the right time.
我们必须要在正确的时间站在正确的位置上
Then, and only then, can the door be opened.
那时 也只有那时 我们才能打开大门
So this is...
所以...
your purpose, to enter the mountain?
你们的目的 就是进入那座山?
What of it?
是又怎样?
There are some who would not deem it wise.
一定有人不赞同这种做法
What do you mean?
你是什么意思?
You are not the only guardian to stand watch over Middle-earth.
你不是中土世界唯一的守护者
Not with your...
没和你的同伴...
companions?
在一起?
Uh, no, I shan't be missed.
呃 没有 应该没人会记得我的
The truth is that most of them don't think I should be on this journey.
其实大部分人都觉得我根本不应该参加这次旅行
Indeed?
真的吗?
I've heard that Hobbits are very resilient.
我听说霍比特人都很有毅力
Really?
真的?
Mm.
嗯
I've also heard they're fond of the comforts of home.
我还听说他们都很喜欢家的温暖
I've heard that it's unwise to seek the council of Elves.
我听说精灵的意见一点也不明智
That they will answer with yes and no.
他们的回答总是模棱两可
You are very welcome to stay here, if that...
如果你愿意的话...
is your wish.
我们非常欢迎你留在这里
No, you did the same thing. It's not like you didn't do it.
不 你也干过这样的事 你肯定也干过
Dori! Here, take that.
朵力! 给 接住它!
Bombur!
庞博!
Of course I was going to tell you. I was waiting...
我当然敢说 我等这个机会...
for this very chance. And really, I think you can trust that I know what I am doing.
已经等了很久了 而且 我觉得你应该相信 我知道我在做什么
Do you? That dragon has slept...
是吗? 那条巨龙已经沉睡了...
for 60 years.
六十年了
What will happen if your plan should fail...
如果你唤醒那个巨兽...
- if you wake that beast?  - What if we succeed?
- 但是你的计划失败...  - 万一我们成功了呢?
If the Dwarves take back the mountain...
如果矮人夺回那座山
our defenses in the east will be strengthened.
我们在东部的防线就会加强
It is a dangerous move, Gandalf.
这一步走的太险了 甘道夫
It is also dangerous to do nothing.
什么都不做也很危险
Oh, come, the throne of Erebor is Thorin's birthright. What is it you fear?
拜托 伊鲁柏的皇冠本来就是属于索林的 你在怕什么?
Have you forgotten?
你不记得了吗?
A strain of madness runs deep in that family.
他们家族有发疯的病史
His grandfather lost his mind. His father succumbed to...
他的祖父就变得神志不清 他父亲也是被...
the same sickness.
同样的疾病缠身
Can you swear Thorin Oakenshield...
你敢说 索林・橡木盾...
will not also fall?
就不会这样吗?
Gandalf, these decisions do not rest with us alone. It is not...
甘道夫 我们无需作出这样的决定 中土世界的格局...
up to you or me to redraw the map of Middle-earth.
不是你我能改变的
With or without our help, these Dwarves will march on the mountain.
不管有没有我们的帮助 这些矮人都会向着那座山前进
They're determined to reclaim their homeland.
他们决心要收复家园
I do not believe Thorin Oakenshield feels that he is answerable to anyone.
索林・橡木盾认为做这件事 不需要向任何人交代
Nor, for that matter, am I.
我也这么认为
It is not me you must answer to.
你不需要向我交待
Lady Galadriel.
凯兰崔尔夫人
Mithrandir.
米斯兰迪尔
I had no idea Lord Elrond had sent for you.
我不知道爱隆请来了您
He didn't.
他没有
I did.
是我请的
Ah.
哦
Saruman.
萨鲁曼
You've been busy of late, my friend.
你最近好像很忙 我的朋友
Tell me, Gandalf...
告诉我 甘道夫...
did you think these plans and schemes of yours...
你是不是觉得你的计划和方案...
would go unnoticed?
会无人知晓?
Unnoticed?
无人知晓?
No.
不
I'm simply doing what I feel to be right.
我只是在做我认为对的事情
The dragon has long been on your mind.
那条龙一直让你耿耿于怀
That is true, my lady.
确实是 夫人
Smaug owes allegiance to no one.
史矛革不会听命于任何人
But if he should side with The Enemy...
但是如果他和大敌站在一边...
a dragon could be used to terrible effect.
这条龙会发挥出极其可怕的作用
What enemy?
什么敌人?
Gandalf, The Enemy is defeated.
甘道夫 大敌已经被打败了
Sauron is vanquished. He can never regain his full strength.
索伦被击溃了 他不可能再恢复原来的力量
Does it not worry you that the last of the Dwarf rings...
你难道从来就没想过 难道最后一枚矮人之戒...
should simply vanish...
真的随着它的主人...
along with its bearer?
一起消失了吗?
Of the seven Dwarf rings, four were consumed by dragons...
矮人七戒中有四枚毁于巨龙之焰...
two were taken by Sauron before he fell in Mordor.
索伦坠入魔多之前拿了两枚
The fate of the last Dwarf ring remains unknown.
最后一枚矮人之戒的下落却无人知晓
The ring that was worn by Thrain.
也就是索恩戴着的那枚戒指
Without the ruling Ring of Power...
没有至尊魔戒...
the seven are of no value to The Enemy.
那七戒对于大敌来说也毫无用处
To control...
要控制...
the other rings...
其他的戒指...
he needs the One.
他就需要那唯一一枚魔戒
And that ring was lost long, long ago.
而魔戒在很久很久之前就已经消失了
It was swept out...
它被安都因河的水...
to sea by the waters of the Anduin.
冲向了大海
Gandalf, for 400 years we have lived in peace...
甘道夫 四百年来我们一直生活在和平之中...
a hard-won...
我们小心翼翼维持着...
watchful peace.
这来之不易的和平
Are we? Are we at peace?
是吗? 我们生活在和平之中吗?
Trolls have come down from the mountains. They are raiding villages, destroying farms.
食人妖从山上来到平原 他们洗劫村庄 摧毁农田
Orcs have attacked us on the road.
半兽人在路上袭击了我们
Hardly a prelude to war.
这些并不是大战的序幕
Always you must meddle...
你总是喜欢多管闲事...
looking for trouble where none exists.
杞人忧天
Let him speak.
让他说下去
There is something at work beyond the evil of Smaug.
还有一种超越史矛革的邪恶势力在活动
Something far more powerful.
一种更加强大的力量
We can remain blind to it, but it will not be ignoring us, that I can promise you.
我们可以视而不见 但是我敢保证 它绝对不会放过我们
A sickness lies over the Greenwood.
巨绿森林里藏着一股邪恶的力量
The woodsmen who live there now call it Mirkwood.
住在森林里的樵夫 改称那儿为幽暗密林
And they say...
他们说...
Well?
说什么?
Don't stop now.
别停啊
Tell us what the woodsmen say.
告诉我们樵夫是怎么说的
They speak of a Necromancer...
他们说有个死灵法师
living in Dol Guldur.
住在多尔戈多
A sorcerer who can summon the dead.
他会召唤亡灵
That's absurd.
真是荒唐
No such power exists in this world.
这世间根本没这种力量
This Necromancer is nothing more than a mortal man.
这个死灵法师不过是一个凡人
A conjurer dabbling in black magic.
一个涉足黑魔法的方士罢了
And so I thought too.
我也是这么想的
- But Radagast has seen...  - Radagast?
- 但是瑞达加斯特看到...  - 瑞达加斯特?
Do not speak to me of Radagast the Brown.
别跟我提褐袍瑞达加斯特
He's a foolish fellow.
他很愚蠢
Well, he's odd, I grant you. He lives a solitary life.
我同意 他确实有点奇怪 因为他过着隐居生活
It's not that. It's his excessive...
不是因为这个 肯定是他...
consumption of mushrooms.
过分食用迷幻蘑菇
They've addled his brain...
导致神志不清...
and yellowed his teeth.
牙齿发黄
I've warned him.
我警告过他
It is unbefitting one of the Istari to be wandering the woods...
一个巫师老是在森林里闲逛可没有好处...
You carry something.
你带着一件东西
It came to you from Radagast.
是瑞达加斯特给你的
He found it in Dol Guldur.
他在多尔戈多找到的
Yes.
是
Show me.
拿出来
listen to me.
听我说
I would think I was talking to myself for all the attention that he paid.
他根本就没仔细听 我都觉得是我在自言自语了
By all means...
无论如何...
What is that?
那是什么?
A relic of Mordor.
是魔多的遗迹
A Morgul Blade.
魔古尔剑
Made for the Witchking of Angmar.
是为安格玛巫王所铸
And buried with him.
并随他下葬
When Angmar fell...
安格玛死后
the Men of the North took his body...
北方的人类带走了他的遗体...
and all that he possessed and sealed it within the High Fells of Rhudaur.
和所有的遗产 葬于鲁道尔群山
Deep within the rock they buried him...
他们将他葬在山下...
in a tomb so dark...
墓穴深埋...
it would never come to light.
永无天日
This is not possible.
这不可能
A powerful spell lies upon those tombs.
墓穴里有强大的魔咒
They cannot be opened.
是不可能被打开的
What proof do we have this weapon came from Angmar's grave?
你有什么证据证明这把剑出自安格玛的坟墓?
I have none.
没有证据
Because there is none.
因为这根本就是臆想
Let us examine what we know.
我来说说现在知道些什么
A single Orc pack...
一群半兽人...
has dared to cross the Bruinen.
胆大妄为 穿越了布鲁南河
A dagger from a bygone age has been found.
一把古老的匕首
And a human sorcerer who calls himself "The Necromancer"...
还有一个住在废弃堡垒里...
has taken up residence in a ruined fortress.
自称是"死灵法师"的人类方士
It's not so very much after all.
算算也没多少
The question of this Dwarvish company, however...
但对这群矮人...
troubles me deeply.
我深感忧虑
I'm not convinced, Gandalf.
你还没有说服我 甘道夫
I do not feel I can condone such a quest.
我觉得我无法容忍这次远征
If they'd come to me, I might have spared them this disappointment.
如果他们来找我 我就不会先让他们有希望 再失望
I do not pretend to understand your reason for raising their hopes.
我没法假装自己明白你燃起他们希望的缘由
They are leaving.
他们走了
Yes.
没错
You knew.
你早就计划好了
No, I'm afraid there is...
不 我想这件事...
nothing else for it.
没有其他意义了
My Lord Elrond.
爱隆殿下
The Dwarves, they're gone.
那些矮人走了
Be on your guard.
大家提高警惕
We're about to step over the Edge of the Wild.
我们马上就要走出边境了
Balin, you know these paths. Lead on.
巴林 你认识路 你走最前面
Aye.
好
Master Baggins...
巴金斯先生...
I suggest you keep up.
我建议你快跟上
You will follow them.
你会跟随他们
Yes.
是
You are right to help Thorin Oakenshield.
帮助索林・橡木盾是对的
But I fear this quest has set in motion...
但我怕这次远征会唤出...
forces we do not yet understand.
那些未知的势力
The riddle of the Morgul Blade must be answered.
魔古尔剑为何出现 必须找到原因
Something moves in the shadows unseen, hidden from our sight.
有股势力正在暗处滋长 避开了我们的耳目
It will not show itself.
他们不会轻易现身
Not yet.
还不会
But every day it grows in strength.
但他们的力量与日俱增
You must be careful.
你得小心
Mithrandir?
米斯兰迪尔?
Why the Halfling?
为什么选了半身人?
I do not know.
我不知道
Saruman believes that it is only great power...
萨鲁曼认为只有拥有强大力量的人...
that can hold evil in check.
才能与邪恶对抗
But that is not what I have found.
但我不敢苟同
I have found it is the small things...
我发现真正驱走黑暗的...
everyday deeds of ordinary folk...
是平凡的人们
that keeps the darkness at bay.
怀着仁慈与爱意之心
Simple acts of kindness and love.
所做的平凡而微小的事迹
Why Bilbo Baggins?
为什么选了比尔博・巴金斯?
Perhaps it is because I'm afraid...
也许是因为我感到害怕...
and he gives me courage.
而他给了我勇气
Do not be afraid, Mithrandir.
别害怕 米斯兰迪尔
You are not alone.
你不是孤身一人
Hey! Hold on!
小心! 抓紧了
Aah!
啊!
Bilbo!
比尔博!
We must find...
我们得找个...
shelter!
避雨的地方!
Look out!
小心!
Look out, brother!
小心 兄弟!
Hold on!
抓紧!
This is no thunderstorm.
这根本不是雷暴
It's a thunder-battle!
这是场战争!
Look!
看!
Well, bless me.
天啊
The legends are true.
传说是真的
Giants! Stone-Giants!
巨人! 石头巨人!
Take cover, you fool!
躲好 傻瓜!
Hold on!
抓紧!
What's happening?
怎么回事?
Grab my hand!
抓住我的手!
Go, go, go!
快 快 快!
Run! Get off!
快跑! 跳过去!
Get off!
跳过去!
- Run!  - Hold on!
- 快跑!  - 小心!
Look out!
小心!
Jump!
跳!
Come on!
快点!
Hold on!
抓紧!
No!
不!
Kili!
奇力!
It's all right! They're alive!
没事! 他们还活着!
Where's Bilbo?
比尔博在哪?
Where's the Hobbit?
那个霍比特人呢?
There!
在那!
Get him!
快去拉他!
Aah!
啊!
Grab my hand!
抓住我的手!
Bilbo!
比尔博!
Ori, be careful!
欧力 小心!
Take it!
抓住!
I've got you, lad.
我抓牢你了 伙计
Grab on! Grab on!
抓紧! 抓紧!
Come on.
快
Get him.
抓紧他
Come on, lad. Up you get.
加油 伙计 爬上来
I thought we'd lost our burglar.
我以为我们的飞贼会死呢
He's been lost ever since he left home.
他离开家乡就死定了
He should never have come.
他就不该跟着我们
He has no place amongst us.
他在我们中间没有位置
Dwalin!
德瓦林!
It looks safe enough.
看上去挺安全的
Search to the back.
到深处搜查一下
Caves in the mountain are seldom unoccupied.
山洞往往都是有主人的
There's nothing here.
这儿什么都没有
Right, then. Let's get a fire started.
那好吧 大家生火
No. No fires. Not in this place.
不 在这儿不能生火
Get some sleep.
大家休息一会
We start at first light.
天一亮 我们就出发
We were to wait in the mountains until Gandalfjoined us.
我们应该在山里等着甘道夫来汇合
That was the plan.
这是计划
Plans change.
计划变了
Bofur, take the first watch.
波佛 你守第一岗
Where do you think...
你要...
you're going?
去哪儿?
Back to Rivendell.
回瑞文戴尔去
No, no, you can't turn back now, eh?
不 不 你不能现在回去 对吧?
You're part of the company.
你属于远征队
You're one of us.
是我们中的一员
I'm not, though, am I?
但我不是 对吧?
Thorin said I should never have come and he was right.
索林说我就不该跟来的 他说对了
I'm not a Took...
我不姓图克...
I'm a Baggins. I don't know what I was thinking.
我姓巴金斯 不知道当时我在想什么
I should never have run out my door.
我就不该出家门的
You're homesick. I understand.
你想家了 我明白
No, you don't. You don't understand. None of you do.
不 你一点都不明白 你们都不明白
You're Dwarves. You're used to this life.
你们是矮人 习惯了这种生活
To living on the road...
风餐露宿...
never settling in one place, not belonging anywhere!
居无定所 毫无归宿!
Oh, I am sorry. I didn't...
哦 抱歉 我无意...
No, you're right.
不 你说得对
We don't belong anywhere.
我们没有归宿
I wish you all the luck in the world.
我祝你能一路顺风
I really do.
是真心的
What's that?
那是什么?
Hmm?
什么?
Wake up!
快醒醒!
Whoa!
哇!
Look out! Look out!
小心! 小心！
Get away!
滚!
Filthy scum!
肮脏的畜生!
Get back!
退后!
You'll pay for this!
你会付出代价的!
Got you.
抓住你了
All right, all right.
好吧 好吧
Get off! Get your hands off me! Get off me!
放开我! 把你的手拿开! 放开我!
Get off me!
放开我!
I feel a song coming on.
我想出了一首歌
# Clap, snap, the black crack #
# 喀拉 噼啪 黑色裂缝咔嚓嚓 #
# Grip, grab, pinch and nab #
# 一抓 二拉 捉过来了捏着耍 #
# Batter and beat #
# 梆梆捣烂继续打 #
# Make'em stammer and #
# 让他们结巴 #
# Squeak #
# 叫得哇哇哇 #
# Pound, pound, far #
# 绕来 绕去 远远 #
# Underground #
# 在地下 #
# Down, down, down in Goblin-town #
# 哥布林城深深埋地下 #
# With a swish and a smack and a whip and a crack #
# 呼咻 啪啦 鞭子抽打 #
# Everybody talks when they're on my rack #
# 人人上了我的刑台都爱说话 #
# Pound,pound, far underground #
# 绕来 绕去 远远在地下 #
# Down, down, down in Goblin-town #
# 哥布林城深深埋地下 #
# Hammer and tongs get out your knockers and gongs #
# 拿出锤子 举起钳子 带上凿子和铜锣 #
# You won't last long on the end of my prong #
# 在我的叉齿上你活不了多长 #
# Clash, crash #
# 咚咙 哐啷 #
# Crush and smash #
# 哗啦 啪嗒 #
# Bang, break, shiver and shake #
# 乒乒乓乓 吓得你全身打架 #
# You can yammer and yelp, but there ain't no help#
# 任你抱怨大吼 没人会来搭救 #
# Pound, pound, far underground #
# 绕来 绕去 远远在地下 #
# Down, down, down in Goblin... #
# 哥布林城深深... #
# Town #
# 埋地下 #
Yeah!
耶!
Catchy, isn't it?
好听吧?
It's one of my own compositions.
我自己作曲的
That's not a song.
这哪里是歌
It's an abomination!
简直糟糕透顶!
Abomination.
糟糕
Mutations. Deviations.
古怪 差异
That's all you're gonna find down here.
这地底下满是这些东西
Who would be so bold as to come armed into my kingdom?
是谁胆敢全副武装 闯进我的王国?
Spies?
是间谍?
Thieves?
小偷?
Assassins?
还是杀手?
Dwarves, Your Malevolence.
是矮人 陛下
Dwarves?
矮人?
We found them on the Front Porch.
我们在入口那里抓到的
Well, don't just stand there. Search them.
那就别傻站着 搜他们的身
Every crack.
角角落落
Every crevice.
好好搜搜
It is my belief...
我相信...
your great protuberance, that they...
尊贵的大王 他们...
are in league with Elves!
和精灵是一伙的!
"Made in Rivendell. " Ah.
"瑞文戴尔铸造" 啊
Second Age. Couldn't give it away.
第二纪的东西 送也送不掉
Just a couple of keepsakes.
只是些纪念品
What are you doing in these parts?
你们到我的地盘上做什么?
Uh, don't worry, lads. I'll handle this.
别担心 兄弟们 我来处理
What's... What's that?
他... 他要做什么?
No tricks. I want the truth, warts and all.
不准耍花招 我要听实话 毫无隐瞒
You're going to have to speak up.
麻烦再说响一点
Your boys flattened my trumpet.
你的手下踩扁了我的助听喇叭
I'll flatten more than your trumpet!
我会踩扁的可不止你的喇叭!
If it's more information you want, I'm the one you should speak to.
如果你要更多消息 就该跟我谈
Mm-hm.
嗯哼
We were on the road. Well, it's not so much a road as a path.
我们本来在路上走 不是大路啦 比较像小路
It's not even that, come to think of it. More like a track.
其实想想 连小路也算不上 顶多是条小径
Anyway, the point is, we were on this road, like a path, like a track.
重点是 我们在这条像小路 又像小径的路上走
And then we weren't, which is a problem, because we were...
结果就遇到了问题 因为我们本该...
- supposed to be in Dunland...  - Shut up.
- 在上礼拜二...  - 闭嘴
last Tuesday.
就到登兰德的(离此处脚程约...1个月)
Visiting distant relations.
是去拜访远亲
Some inbreds on me mother's side.
我妈妈那边的亲戚
Shut up!
闭嘴!
If they will not talk, we'll make them squawk.
如果他们不开口 我们就想办法撬开他们的嘴
Bring up the mangler.
把绞肉机搬过来
Bring up the bonebreaker.
还有碎骨锤
Start with the youngest.
从最年轻的开始
Wait!
等等!
Well, well, well.
哎呀 看看 看看
Look who it is.
看看是谁来了
Thorin, son of Thrain, son of Thror...
原来是索林呀 索恩之子 索尔之孙...
King Under the Mountain.
山丘之王
Oh, but I'm forgetting. You don't have a mountain.
哦 但我忘了 你已经没有山了
And you're not a king...
也不是国王...
which makes you...
那你其实就是个...
nobody, really.
无名小卒
I know someone who would pay a pretty price for your head.
我知道有人悬赏了一笔可观的赏金 要买你的脑袋
Just a head.
就一颗脑袋
Nothing attached.
别的不要
Perhaps you know of whom I speak.
也许你知道我说的是谁
An old enemy of yours.
你的宿敌
A pale Orc, astride a white Warg.
骑着白色座狼的苍白半兽人
Azog the Defiler was destroyed.
毁灭者阿索格已经死了
He was slain in battle long ago.
他在很久之前的一战中已经死了
So you think his defiling days are done, do you?
所以你觉得他已经不能兴风作浪了 对吧?
Send word to the pale Orc.
给苍白半兽人传话
Tell him I have found his prize.
跟他说我抓到了他要的人
Yes.
好
Yes!
太棒了!
Gollum, gollum!
咕噜 咕噜!
Aah!
啊!
Nasty Goblinses!
恶心的哥布林!
Better than old bones, precious.
但总比陈年骨头好 宝贝
Better than nothing.
总比没有的好
Too many boneses, precious. Not enough flesh!
骨头太多了 宝贝 都没多少肉!
Shut up! Cut its skin off.
闭嘴! 把它的皮扒下来
Start with its head.
从它的头开始
# The cold hard lands. They bites our hands #
# 冰冷的地面 磨破了我们的手 #
# They gnaws our feet #
# 折磨着我们的脚 #
# The rocks and stones. They're like old bones #
# 岩石和石块 就跟陈骨头一般 #
# All bare of meat #
# 根本没有肉 #
# Cold as death. Without no breath #
# 冰冷如尸体 全无气息 #
# It's good to eat #
# 就能吃了 #
Bless us and splash us...
神还真是保佑我们...
precious.
宝贝
That's a meaty mouthful.
这只看上去有好多肉
Gollum, gollum! Aah.
咕噜 咕噜! 啊
Back. Stay back.
退后 快退后
I'm warning you...
我警告你...
don't come any closer.
别靠近我
It's got an Elfish blade.
他有一把精灵的剑
But it's not an Elfs.
但他不是精灵
Not an Elfs, no.
不是精灵 不是
What is it, precious?
那他是什么 宝贝?
What is it?
是什么?
My name is Bilbo Baggins.
我叫比尔博・巴金斯
Bagginses?
巴金斯?
What is a Bagginses, precious?
什么是巴金斯 宝贝?
- I'm a Hobbit from the Shire.  - Oh.
- 我是住在夏尔的霍比特人  - 哦
We like Goblinses, batses and fishes. But we hasn't tried Hobbitses before.
我们喜欢哥布林 蝙蝠和鱼 但我们没吃过霍比特人
Is it soft? Is it juicy?
鲜嫩吗? 多汁吗?
Now, now...
退后...
keep your distance!
别靠近我!
I'll use this if I have to.
你再靠近 我就动手了
Aah!
啊!
I don't want any trouble.
我不想惹麻烦
Do you understand?
你懂吗?
Just show me the way to get out of here and I'll be on my way.
你只要给我指条出去的路 我马上就走
Why? Is it lost?
怎么了? 他迷路了吗?
Yes. Yes, and I want to get unlost as soon as possible.
没错 但我想快点找到路
Ooh, we knows! We knows safe paths for Hobbitses.
哦 我懂! 我知道一条安全的路
Safe paths in...
在黑暗里的...
the dark. Shut up!
安全小道 闭嘴!
I didn't say anything.
我没开口
We wasn't talking to you.
我们没在跟你说话
Oh, yes, we was, precious. We was.
不 宝贝 我们的确在跟他说话
Look, I don't know what your game is...
听着 我不知道你在玩什么游戏...
but I...
但我...
Games?
游戏?
Oh, we love games, doesn't we, precious?
哦 我们就喜欢玩游戏 对吧 宝贝?
Does it like games? Does it, does it?
看上去像游戏吗? 像吗 像吗?
Does it like to play?
他想玩吗?
Maybe.
也许吧
What has roots as nobody sees?
什么东西有根 却没人看得见?
Is taller than trees?
比树还高?
Up, up, up it goes
直上云霄
And yet
但却
Never grows
从不生长
The mountain.
是山
Yes, yes.
对 猜对了
Oh, let's have another one, eh?
再猜一个 好吗?
Yes! Do it again.
对! 再猜一个
Do it again. Ask us.
这回你来问
No! No more riddles.
不! 别猜谜了
Finish him off.
杀了他
Finish him now! Gollum, gollum!
快杀了他! 咕噜 咕噜!
No! No. No.
不! 等等
No. I want to play. I do.
等等 我想玩 真的想
I want to play. I can see...
我想玩 我看得出...
you are very good at this.
你很擅长猜谜
So why don't we...
所以我们...
have a game of riddles? Yes?
再玩玩猜谜吧? 怎么样?
Just you and me.
就我们两个
Yes. Yes, just us.
好 好 就我们
Yes. Yes.
好 就这样
And if I win...
如果我赢了...
you show me the way out. Yes?
你就带我出去 好吗?
Yes. Yes.
好 好
And if it loses?
如果他输了呢?
What then?
怎么办?
Well, if it loses, precious, then we eats it.
如果他输了 宝贝 我们就吃了他
If Baggins loses, we eats it whole.
如果巴金斯输了 我们就吞了他
Fair enough.
很公平
Well, Baggins first.
好 巴金斯先出谜题
Thirty white horses on a red hill
红山岗上有三十匹白马
First they champ
它们咀嚼
Then they stamp
它们跺脚
Then they stand still
然后停住不动了
Teeth?
牙齿?
Teeth!
是牙齿!
Oh, yes, my precious!
猜对了 我的宝贝!
But we... We...
但是我们...
only have nine.
我们只有九颗
Our turn.
该我们了
Voiceless, it cries
没有声音 却能呼啸
Wingless flutters
没有翅膀 却能振翼
Toothless bites
没有牙齿 却能噬咬
Mouthless
没有嘴巴
Mutters
却能低泣
Just a minute.
等一下
Uh...
呃...
Oh. Oh!
哦 哦!
We knows! We knows!
我们知道了! 我们知道!
Shut up!
闭嘴!
Wind.
风
It's wind.
是风
Of course it is.
当然了
Very clever...
非常聪明...
Hobbitses.
霍比特人
Very clever.
非常聪明
Ah-ah-ah.
啊啊啊
A box without hinges
盒子没有铰链
Key or lid
钥匙或盖子
Yet golden treasure
却能藏起
Inside is hid
金黄色的宝藏
Box.
盒子
Oh, um...
哦 呃...
Box. The lid and a key.
盒子 盖子和钥匙
Well?
怎么样?
It's nasty.
真讨厌
Box. Key.
盒子 钥匙
Do you give up?
你放弃吗?
Give us a chance, precious! Give us a chance!
给我们一次机会 宝贝! 给我们一个机会!
Eggses!
鸡蛋!
Wet, crunchy...
潮湿 易碎的...
little eggses. Yes.
小鸡蛋 没错
Grandmother taught us...
祖母教过我们...
to suck them, yes!
怎么吮吸它们 是的!
We have one...
我们有个谜题
for you.
要给你
All things it devours
它吞食一切
Birds, beasts
飞鸟 野兽
Trees, flowers
树木 鲜花
Gnaws iron
啃食铁
Bites steel
咬断钢
Grinds hard stones to meal
研磨坚石成食粮
Answer us.
回答我们
Give me a moment, please. I gave you a good long while.
让我想想 拜托 我给了你很长时间
Birds, beasts... Beasts? Trees, flowers.
飞鸟 野兽... 野兽? 树木 鲜花
I don't know this one.
我不知道这个了
Is it tasty?
他可口吗?
Is it scrumptious?
他美味吗?
Is it crunchable?
他清脆吗?
Let me think.
让我想想
It's stuck.
他卡壳了
Bagginses is stuck.
巴金斯卡壳了
Time's up.
时间到
Time.
时间
The answer...
答案是...
is time.
是时间
Actually it wasn't that hard.
其实也没那么难嘛
Last question.
最后一个问题
Last chance.
最后一次机会
Okay.
好吧
Ask us.
问我们吧
Ask us!
问我们!
Yes, yes. All right.
好 好 好吧
What have I got...
我口袋里...
in my pocket?
是什么?
That's no fair.
这不公平
It's not fair! It's against...
这不公平! 这是违反...
the rules!
规则的!
Now ask us another one.
现在换个问题问我们
No. No, no, no.
不 不行 不行
You said ask me a question. Well, that is my question.
你说问我一个问题 那么 这就是我的问题
What have I got in my pocket?
我口袋里有什么?
Three guesses, precious. It must give us...
猜三次 宝贝 你必须给我们...
three!
三次机会!
Three guesses. Very well, guess away.
猜三次 那好吧 尽管猜
- Handses!  - Wrong.
- 手!  - 错了
Guess again.
再猜
Fishbones, Goblins' teeth, wet shells, bats' wings...
鱼骨头 哥布林的牙齿 湿壳 蝙蝠翅膀...
Knife! Oh, shut up!
是匕首! 哦 闭嘴!
Wrong again. Last guess.
又错了 最后一次
String.
绳子
Or nothing.
或者什么都没有
Two guesses at once. Wrong both times.
一下猜了两次 两次都错了
So...
那么...
Come, then. I won the game.
那就来吧 我赢了比赛
You promised to show me the way out.
你答应过带我出去的
Did we say so, precious?
我们这么说过吗 宝贝?
Did we say so?
我们是这么说的吗?
What has it got in its pocketses?
他口袋里装了什么?
That's no concern of yours.
这不关你的事
You lost.
你输了
Lost?
输了?
Where is it?
它在哪儿?
Where is it?!
它在哪儿?!
No!
不!
Lost!
丢了!
Curse us and splash us!
诅咒我们 唾骂我们吧!
My precious...
我的宝贝...
is lost!
丢了!
What have you lost?
你丢了什么?
Mustn't ask us! Not its business!
不许问我们! 不关你的事!
No! Gollum!
不! 咕噜!
Gollum!
咕噜!
What has it got...
他放了什么...
in its nasty...
在他肮脏的...
little pocketses?
小口袋里?
He stole it.
他偷了它
He stole it!
他偷了它!
# Bones will be shattered #
# 打碎你的骨头 #
# Necks will be wrung #
# 拧断你的脖子 #
# You'll be beaten and battered #
# 打得屁滚尿流 #
# From racks you'll be hung #
# 悬挂到绞刑架上 #
# You will die down here #
# 你会死于此处 #
# And never be found #
# 永不见天日 #
# Down in the deep of Goblin-town #
# 在这幽深的 #
# Of Goblin-town #
# 哥布林城 #
I know that sword!
我认识这把剑!
It is the Goblin-cleaver!
这是哥布林斩杀者!
The Biter!
咬剑!
The blade that sliced...
这把剑砍下了...
a thousand necks! Slash them!
一千个哥布林的头! 猛砍他们!
Beat them! Kill them!
鞭打他们! 杀了他们!
Kill them all!
一个不剩!
Cut off his head!
割掉他的头!
Take up arms.
拿起武器
Fight.
战斗
Fight!
战斗!
He wields the Foehammer! The Beater!
他挥舞着敌击剑! 击剑!
Bright as daylight!
如白昼般明亮!
Thorin!
索林!
Follow me.
跟我来
Quick!
快!
Run!
快跑!
Give it to us!
还给我们!
It's...
它是...
ours.
我们的
It's ours!
它是我们的!
Thief!
小偷!
Baggins!
巴金斯!
Quickly!
快!
Faster!
加速!
Post!
前进!
Charge!
向前冲!
Cut the ropes!
砍断绳子!
Come on, quickly!
快走 快!
- Come on, move!  - Bombur!
- 跟上 快走!  - 庞博!
Go, go, go!
快 快 快!
Jump!
跳!
Jump, lad!
快跳 老弟!
Come on!
快点!
Push!
推!
Watch your backs!
小心背后!
You thought you could escape me.
还想逃过我的手心
What are you going to do now, Wizard?
你现在还想干什么 巫师?
That'll do it.
还真有两下子
Well, that could have been worse.
好了 这还不算最糟的呢
Haver!
乌鸦嘴!
You've got to be joking!
开什么玩笑!
Gandalf!
甘道夫!
There's too many. We can't fight them.
他们太多了 我们打不过
Only one thing will save us, daylight!
只有一样东西可以救我们 阳光!
Come on!
快点!
Here! On your feet.
抓住我! 站起来
- Balin.  - Come on!
- 巴林  - 快!
Wait!
慢着!
My precious. Wait!
我的宝贝 等等我!
Gollum, gollum!
咕噜 咕噜!
Quick, quick!
快 快!
This way.
这边
- Come on.  - Come on, come on. Quickly.
- 跟上  - 快 跟上 快
Right, good!
没错 很好!
Baggins!
巴金斯!
Thief!
小偷!
Curse it and crush it! We hates it forever!
诅咒他粉碎他! 我们永远恨他!
Five, six, seven, eight.
五 六 七 八
Bifur. Bofur. That's 10.
毕佛 波佛 十个了
Fili, Kili! That's 12.
菲力 奇力! 十二个
And Bombur. That makes 13.
还有庞博 加起来十三个
Where's Bilbo?
比尔博去哪了?
Where is our Hobbit?
我们的霍比特人呢?
Curse that Halfling!
诅咒那个半身人!
Now he's lost?
现在他丢了?
I thought he was with Dori!
我以为他和朵力在一起!
Don't blame me!
别怪我!
Where did you last see him?
你最后见他是在哪?
I think I saw him...
我记得他...
slip away...
第一次被包围时...
when they first collared us.
就溜走了
And what happened, exactly?
到底发生了什么?
- Tell me!  - I'll tell you what happened.
- 告诉我!  - 我来告诉你发生了什么
Master Baggins saw his chance...
巴金斯先生趁乱...
and he took it.
逃走了
He has thought of nothing but his soft bed and his warm hearth...
自从他踏出家门...
since first he stepped out of his door.
他一心只想柔软的床和温暖的壁炉
We will not be seeing our Hobbit again.
我们不会再见到我们的霍比特人了
He is long gone.
他早就走远了
No.
不
He isn't.
他没有
Bilbo Baggins.
比尔博・巴金斯
I have never been so glad...
我这辈子从没有...
to see anyone in my life.
这么高兴见到谁过
Bilbo.
比尔博
We'd given you up.
我们都放弃你了
How on earth did you get past the Goblins?
你是怎么逃出来的?
How, indeed.
真的 怎么会
Well, what does it matter? He's back.
这个 有什么关系呢? 他回来就好
It matters.
有关系
I want to know.
我想知道
Why did you come back?
你为什么回来?
Look, I know you doubt me. I know you always have.
听着 我知道你不信任我 一直都是
And you're right. I often think of Bag-end.
而你是对的 我经常想念我的袋底洞
I miss my books.
想念我的书
And my armchair and my garden.
还有我的扶手椅 我的花园
See, that's where I belong.
懂了吧 那才是我的归属
That's home.
我的家
And that's why I came back. Because...
这也是我回来的原因 因为...
you don't have one. A home.
你们还没有家
It was taken from you.
它被人侵占了
But I will help you take it back if I can.
但我会帮你们夺回来的 尽我的能力
Out of the frying pan.
才出虎口
And into the fire. Run.
又入狼窝 跑
Run!
快跑!
Go!
快!
Up into the trees!
上树!
All of you!
所有人!
Climb! Bilbo, climb!
爬树! 比尔博 快爬!
Quickly!
快点!
They're coming!
他们要来了!
- Hang on!  - Hold on, brothers!
- 抓紧!  - 抓紧 兄弟们!
Azog.
阿索格
It cannot be.
不可能
It's going!
树倒了!
Fili!
菲力!
Yeah!
好哎!
No!
不!
Oh, no.
哦 不
Mr. Gandalf!
甘道夫先生!
Oh, no, Dori!
哦 别乱动 朵力!
Help!
救命!
No!
不!
Thorin! No!
索林! 不!
Look.
等等
Thorin!
索林!
Thorin.
索林
The Halfling?
半身人呢?
It's all right.
没事了
Bilbo is here.
比尔博在这儿
He's quite safe.
安然无恙
You!
你!
What were you doing?
你那是在干什么?
You nearly got...
你差点...
yourself killed!
害死你自己!
Did I not say...
我说过...
that you would be a burden?
你是个累赘
That you would not survive in the Wild?
我说你不会在荒野中生存
That you had no place amongst us?
我说你在我们中没有位置
I have never been so wrong in all my life.
我这辈子都没有如此大错特错
I am sorry I doubted you.
很抱歉我怀疑过你
No, I would have doubted me too.
不用 要是我也会怀疑的
I'm not a hero...
我不是英雄...
or a warrior.
或者战士
Not even...
连飞贼...
a burglar.
都算不上
Is that what I think it is?
前面是我们的目的地吗?
Erebor...
伊鲁柏...
the Lonely Mountain...
孤山...
the last of the great Dwarf kingdoms...
中土世界矮人的...
of Middle-earth.
最后王国
Our home.
我们的家
A raven!
一只渡鸦!
The birds...
鸟儿...
are returning to the mountain.
正在飞回山上
That, my dear Oin...
我亲爱的欧因...
is a thrush.
那是一只画眉
But we'll take it as a sign.
对我们来说 它是一种象征
A good omen.
一个好的预兆
You're right.
你说的对
I do believe the worst is behind us.
我相信最艰难的时刻已经过去了
# Far over the misty mountains rise #
# 巍峨的雾山耸立远方 #
# Leave us standing upon the height #
# 我们站在与天相接的地方 #
# What was before, we'll see once more #
# 过往的景色 又一次看见 #
# Is our kingdom a distant light #
# 是我们的王国 一点遥远的光 #
# Fiery mountain beneath the moon #
# 月亮之下 沸腾的火山 #
# The words unspoken, we'll be there soon #
# 话未出口 我们即将到达 #
# For home, a song that echoes on #
# 思乡一曲 群山回响 #
# And all who find us will know the tune #
# 听过之人 过耳不忘 #
# Some folk we never forget #
# 有的人我们从未遗忘 #
# Some kind we never forgive #
# 有的人我们绝不原谅 #
# Haven't seen the back of us yet #
# 从未见过我们退却 #
# We'll fight as long as we live #
# 我们将战到生命最后一刻 #
# All eyes on the hidden door #
# 所有目光集中在 #
# To the Lonely Mountain borne #
# 开启孤山的隐蔽之门 #
# We'll ride in the gathering storm #
# 我们在狂风前夜驰骋 #
# Until we get our long-forgotten gold #
# 直到夺回遗忘已久的宝藏 #
# We lay under the misty mountains cold #
# 我们瑟缩在迷雾山脉 #
# In slumbers deep and dreams of gold #
# 沉眠于梦乡的黄金绚烂 #
# We must awake, our lives to make #
# 快快醒来 使命遥远 #
# And in the darkness a torch we hold #
# 在黑暗中举起火把 #
# From long ago when lanterns burned #
# 从很久之前灯笼熄灭 #
# Until this day our hearts have yearned #
# 直到今日 我们的心热切渴盼 #
# Her fate unknown, the Arkenstone #
# 未知命运 阿肯宝石 #
# What was stolen must be returned #
# 失窃之物 势必归还 #
# We must awake and make the day #
# 快快醒来 路途遥远 #
# To find a song for heart and soul #
# 寻找身心的赞歌 #
# Some folk we never forget #
# 有的人我们从未遗忘 #
# Some kind we never forgive #
# 有的人我们绝不原谅 #
# Haven't seen the end of it yet #
# 还未看到结束 #
# We'll fight as long as we live #
# 我们活着就会战斗 #
# All eyes on the hidden door #
# 所有目光集中在 #
# To the Lonely Mountain borne #
# 开启孤山的隐蔽之门 #
# We'll ride in the gathering storm #
# 我们在狂风前夜驰骋 #
# Till we get our long-forgotten gold #
# 直到夺回遗忘已久的宝藏 #
# Far away from misty mountains cold #
# 远离迷雾 群山阴冷 #